本字幕由志愿者义务贡献，采用许可协议
知识共享 署名-非商业性使用-相同方式共享 3.0 美国
Stanford University. >> All right,
斯坦福大学
well, welcome to Lecture number four?
欢迎参加第四节课
No. Yes, four of Stanford CS193P, Fall of 2017.
2017 年秋季学期斯坦福 CS193P 的第四节课
Today, we're gonna continue to talk about Swift.
今天我们会继续学习 Swift
This will be the last we talk about Swift. After this,
这会是最后一节讲 Swift 的课程，在本节课之后
we're pretty much gonna kinda assume you know Swift.
我会默认你们已经掌握 Swift 了
Obviously you'll be learning on the fly as you go, but
当然在之后的课程中你也会学到 Swift
starting next week,
但从下周的课程开始
we're gonna dive right into iOS, UI kit and
我们将会专注于 iOS，UIKit等
all that. So I'm gonna do the quick demo that I postponed
我将会做一个我们上周三留下来的关于
from Wednesday of this mutating keyword that we have
当我们将一个类改为结构体时
to add when we make something a struct versus a class. Then
必须要使用的 mutating 关键字
we're gonna talk about two very important topics today.
接着我会讲今天两个非常重要的主题
Protocols and closures.
协议和闭包
Functions as types of general those two and in between, I'm
以及简单地讲讲函数。期间
gonna talk about string which is important in a way but
我将会讲字符串，字符串也很重要
it's not like the monstrous important topics like
但它不像超级重要的主题，协议和闭包
prototypes and closures are. So start right into that demo
那样重要。那么现在从我们已经做好的
that I had. And I had remembered, we were talking at the time about
示例程序开始。我记得我们那时正在讲
making things a struct and that it's a little different
如何写一个结构体，结构体与类不一样
then a class because that copy on write. Swift needs to know
因为它是写时复制（copy on write）的
when a function might actually modify the thing so
Swift 需要知道一个函数何时会改变变量的值
that it knows to actually make a real copy. So
它才能知道何时应当真正的去复制这个结构体
let's go back here to our app, Concentration, where we were.
那么让我们回到我们的的翻牌游戏
Let's go to Concentration, which if you recall,
来到我们的 Concentration，如果你还记得
we made be a class. A class Concentration. And
我们写了一个类，叫做 Concentration
this could have just as easily been a struct.
并且我们可以很轻松地将它改为一个结构体
I really made it a class just so when we're doing
我将它写做类只是为了当我们在
the initialize and stuff, you could see the difference
做初始化之类的操作时，你可以看出
between Concentration and card because card was a struct and
Concentration 和 Card 的不同，因为 Card 是结构体
Concentration was a class. But there's
而 Concentration 是一个类，但也没有什么
no reason Concentration wouldn't have been a struct.
理由不让 Concentration 成为一个结构体
It's probably, it might even be better as a struct here.
也许这里它是一个结构体的话还会更好一些
Now we don't pass Concentration games around and
我们不会将翻牌游戏到处传递
all that, it just kinda sits in our controller.
它差不多就是一直待在我们的控制器中
Not really a pointer to our model but this would embed
并不是指向模型的指针，但它会将模型
the model there. So it doesn't really matter too much.
嵌入在这里。所以其实没有什么太大影响
But when I change this from class to struct, notice here
但当我将它改为结构体后，注意在这里我
that I get an error. And let's scroll down and here they are,
得到了一个错误。让我们翻下去，这些错误在这里
here's the error and this error is saying,
这些是错误，它说：
cannot assign to property, self is immutable. Why is this
不能给属性赋值，self 是不可改变的。 为什么
saying self is immutable? I'm trying to change the card here
它说 self 是不可改变的？我在尝试改变 card 的值
to say that they've match, for example.
来表示它们是一样的
Well, self is immutable because this function right
self 之所以是不可改变的，是因为这个函数
is not marked mutable, and so it is assumed to not mutate,
没有被标记为可改变的，所提它被默认为是不可改变的
not change this Concentration object. So
不会改变这个 Concentration 对象
of course we need chooseCard to change the Concentration
当然我们需要这个函数改变 Concentration 对象
object cuz it's the main thing. The change of the game,
因为这就是这个函数的主要功能，改变游戏中的值
so all we need to do is add mutable right here, that
所以我们只需要在这里加上 mutable
marks, sorry, mutating, not mutable, you add that here and
抱歉，不是 mutable，应该是 mutating，将它加在这里
that says that this is a mutating function,
表示这是一个可变（mutating）函数
all the errors go away, and we're all good to go.
所以错误都没有了，我们可以继续
Question? >> [INAUDIBLE]
有问题吗? >>[学生提问]
>> Okay, the question is why
>> 好的，他问的问题是为什么
does this not need it?
这个不需要添加 mutating
This is a var. And this var is get and set, so
因为它是一个变量，并且它可以被获取和赋值，所以
Swift already knows this is mutating, cuz it's settable.
Swift 已经知道它是可变的了，因为它是可以被赋值的
If this was get only, then it wouldn't be mutating and
如果它是只能被获取的，那么他就不是可变的，并且
Swift would know that. So for vars, Swift knows. And
Swift 知道它不是可变的。所以对于变量，Swift 是知道的
if it's not a computed var, like look at this var,
如果它不是一个演算型变量（computed var），像这个变量
how does this one know? That's because, well, this one is
它是如何判断是否为可变的呢？这个变量是外部只读的
read only externally but for us it's writable. Here,
但对我们来说它是可以被改变的
anything that's a var it assumed it's writable. If it
在这里所有的变量都是默认可以被改变的
were a let, a let, then it would think it's not writable.
如果它是一个常量（let），它会被认为是不可改变的
So that's how you do mutating, or mutable. If for vars is
所以这就是你们如何处理可变类型，对于变量
whether they're vars or let, or for computer property,
关注它是可变的（var）还是不可变的（let），对于演算属性
#Everybody got all that？
whether it has both get and set. Where we got all that? So
关注它是否可以获取和赋值。大家都听懂了吗
it's only funcs that we have to put that on.
所以只需要将 mutating 放在函数的前面
Yeah, question. >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> [学生提问]
>> Yes, so the question is,
>> 好的，那位同学的问题是
why is this you need to a struct and not a class, why do
为什么你需要一个结构体而不是类，为什么
I need to struct? And that's very important to understand,
我需要一个结构体，理解这个是很重要的
very good question. Structs are value types, not reference
非常好的问题。结构体是值类型而不是引用类型
types. So structs don't live in the heap. As we pass
所以结构体并不是被存储在堆中。当我们传递
the struct around since it's a value type, it gets copied.
结构体的时候，因为它是值类型，它会被复制
Constantly copied everywhere. Pass through a function,
它会不断地复制到很多地方，传递给一个函数
a copy is made. Put in a var, a copy is made. Well,
它被复制了一次，放到一个变量中，它又被复制了一次
soon, that would be incredibly inefficient if it actually
那么，如果每次复制时，它的每一个位（bit）都被复制
copy the bits of this entire thing every time. So instead,
程序就会变得非常低效。 所以 Swift 不那样做
Swift is smart. It only actually copies the bits when
Swift 很聪明。它只复制你设置为可变的
you mutate it. That's called copy-on-write semantics.
那一部分，这就叫做写时复制（copy on write）
This is why structs are different,
这就是结构体不同的原因
because they have that copy-on-write semantics.
因为他们是写时复制的
A class doesn't have that, cuz when you pass a class around,
类不是那样的，因为当你传递一个类时
the class just lives once in the heap,
那个类只在堆中存在一次
and you're passing pointers to it around.
而你是在传递指向它的指针
And there could be 20 pointers to the same object.
那么可能就会有 20 个指针指向同一个对象
Totally different kinda model for memory. So that's why,
这是完全不同的两种内存模型。这就是原因
it's because it's a value type that copy on writes stuff,
是因为结构体是值类型，值类型是写时复制的
that's why we care that it's mutating.
这就是我们关注它是可变的的原因
Let's go back to our slides and talk about the first very,
让我们回到我们的幻灯片，并且开始第一个非常
very important topic today which is protocols.
非常重要的主题，协议（protocol）
It's the fourth pillar of building data structures
那是在 Swift 中建立数据结构的第四支柱
inside of Swift. You already know a lot now about class,
你们已经学到很多关于类、结构体和枚举的知识了
struct and enum. And a protocol is something where
而一个协议就是一个非常简单的
its a very simple concept. A protocol is basically just
概念，它基本上就是一个
a list of methods and vars with no implementation. But
方法和变量的清单，而不包含任何实现
it's the use of having protocols. It's so
但是协议的使用，它在 Swift 语言与运行时
pervasively used throughout the Swift language and
中被普遍的应用
the runtime that makes it so powerful. So first I'm just
让它变得十分强大。那么首先我会
gonna go through a little bit of why we have protocols.
简单讲一下为什么我们要用协议
Then I'll show you the syntax of protocols.
接着我会向你们展示协议的语法
What it looks like to type in a protocol and define one.
协议是什么样子的与如何定义一个协议
Then we'll start talking about the use of protocols.
接下来我会讲如何协议的用法
Where do we use them? Why are they so valuable? So
我们会在哪里用到协议，为何它们这么重要？
let's start with, what protocols are all about?
那么我们现在开始将，协议到底是什么
Protocols are essentially a way for
协议本质是是就是让调用者用任何它想的
callers to call an API with anything they want.
东西调用一个应用程序接口（API）的方法
Any struct, enum, class,
任何结构体，枚举类型，类
it can pass anything they want in. And at the same time
它可以传递任何它想的的参数。并且同时
the receiving method can specify what it really wants.
接收这些参数的方法可以判别它到底是想要什么
So both sides get to do what they want. The receiving thing
这样两边都可以做它们想做的。接收者
gets to say what it wants the thing you're pass in
来决定它应该用你传递给它的参数做什么
to do and the thing passing in can pass whatever it wants as
而传递者可以向它传任何它想传的参数，只要
long as it does that thing. And to do all this all
接受者可以处理被传的参数。而要做到这样
a protocol is, is a list of vars and functions.
协议实际上就是一个变量和函数的清单
That's all a protocol is. It's just a list of them.
这就是协议。就是一个变量和函数的清单
Not an implementation or anything, just a list of them.
不是实现或者其它什么，只是一个清单
And it's how we use them in the API that let's us get this
而是我们如何在应用程序接口中使用它们，让我们得到
behavior of having the callers and the callees.
调用者和被调用者能表达他们想表达
Get to express things the way they want. Now, what
的行为。那么
are protocols good for? They make APIs very flexible and
用协议有什么好处呢？它们让应用程序接口变得非常灵活
expressive, as you're going to see.
并且非常易于表达，你们接着就会感受到
They're super good for blind structured communication.
它们对标准化匿名通讯机制是非常有好处的
Like, remember back to my MVC talk.
就像，还记得我们曾经讲过的 MVC 间的通信吗
The communication between the view and the controller.
视图和控制器之间的通信
All those will, did, shoulds. And the data at count,
那些will, did, should, data, at, count 方法
those kind of communications between a view controller.
那些视图与控制器之间通信的方式
That all had to be blind, because the views are generic
那些都应该是匿名的，因为视图是泛型的
and the controllers are very specific, and protocols is how
而控制器是非常具体的。而协议就是我们如何让
we make that work. It's also great for mandating behavior,
他们工作的。协议也对控制行为有很大用处
for example, in a dictionary, a dictionary's a hash table,
举个例子，在一个字典类型中，一个字典是哈希表（hash table）
raise your hand if you know what a hash table is when I
如果你知道什么事哈希表，请举手
say that. Okay, everybody. Good. So it's a hash table.
好的，所有人都知道。那么它是一个哈希表
So the keys of a dictionary clearly have to be hashable.
所以字典的键（key）应该具有哈希性（hashable）
You have to be able to get a hash value otherwise you can't
你必须要有一个哈希值否则
hash them and put them in as keys of this hash table.
你不能哈希它们，并且将它们放在这个哈希表的键中
Well, protocols let us define dictionary in a way so
协议让我们这样定义字典
that we don't use any keys that aren't hashable.
我们就不能用任何不具哈希性的键
So mandating behavior hashbility, for example,
那么协议在限制键的
of the key it's great for that. It's also great for
可哈希性方面很好用。协议还可以用于
sharing functionality between very disparate types,
在非常不同的类型间共享相同的功能
types that you would never use object oriented inheritance to
这些类型你可能从来不会用面向对象的继承让他们
make them share a base class, but they are very similar, for
共同继承一个基础的类，但它们非常的相像，举个例子
example, string, array, countable range. They are all
字符串，数组，可数区间（countable range）它们都是
collections of things. Now they're completely different.
一些东西的集合。虽然它们完全不同
Come one, a countable range and
一个可数区间和
a string are completely different. But they are both
字符串当然是完全不同的。但是它们都
collections, a string is a collection of characters,
是一个集合。一个字符串是字符的集合
accountable range is a collection of integers if it's
当可数区间是整数的可数区间时
an accountable range of int. So they do share some and
它是一个整数的集合。那么它们的确都有一些共性
protocols has a mechanism to allow you to share that kind
而协议是一种途径让你可以共享那些共性
of similarity without having to have all those thing
而不用让这些东西都
inherit from some kind common base class that knows about
继承一个公共的关于集合的
collections of things. You see what I'm saying? And so
基础类。你能理解我在说什么吗？那么
in a way, protocols provide multiple inheritance. Now,
从一方面来讲，协议提供了多重继承
since protocols are only doing the declaration of the vars
既然协议只是做了变量和函数的声明
and functions, there's no storage of, of those things,
它不负责储存那些东西
so there's no inheritance of data,
所以它不是数据的继承
it's purely just inheritance of,
单纯的只是
inheritance of functionality. All right, as I go
功能的继承。好的，正如我刚刚解释的
through this explanation, it's super important to understand
理解协议只不过是一种类型是非常重要的
that protocols are just a type. Just like a class is
就像类是一种类型
a type, a struct, an enum, a protocol is a type.
结构体，枚举类型，协议是一种类型
A first-class type, just like all the rest of these types,
协议就像其他这些类型一样，是头等类型（first-class type）
that's very important to understand.
理解这是非常重要的
All right, so let's dive into what a protocol is.
好了，我们开始讲协议是什么
There's three parts to a protocol.
一个协议有三个部分
One, there's the declaration of the protocol, just like you
第一部分是协议的声明，就像
have a declaration of a class or an enum or a struct. For
你的类、枚举类型、结构体有各自的声明一样
a protocol, that's just a list of
对于协议来说，那就是一个方法
methods with their arguments and return values and
和它的参数和返回值的清单，和
a list of vars. That's it, that's what a protocol is,
一个变量的清单。就是这样，这就是一个协议
it's a declaration. Second part of a protocol though
它是一个声明。一个协议的第二部分
is a class or a struct or an enum raises its hand and
是一个类、结构体或枚举类型举起手来并且
claims to implement those methods in vars in that
声明要来实现协议中的那些对变量的处理方法
protocol. So there's the claim to implement a protocol,
那么这里有要实现这个协议的声明
that's the second part. Cuz somebody has to actually
这是第二部分。因为有人要真正的去
implement those methods that the protocol is a list of, and
实现协议中列出的那些方法
that's classes, structs and enums, so they have to claim.
而这可以是类、结构体、和枚举类型。所以他们要去声明
And then the third part is the code in those classes,
接着第三部分是是在那些类、结构体和枚举类型中
structs and in in enums that actually implements
的代码，这些代码真正地实现了
the protocol methods in vars. Okay, so
协议中对变量的处理的方法
notice I'm mentioning vars. The vars,
注意到我提到了变量。那些变量
the storage of the vars, if they're not computed vars,
如果他们不是演算变量的话
has to be in some struct, enum or a class. Because,
必须要存储在结构体、枚举类型或或一个类中。因为
that's the only places you can have any storage, all right?
那些是唯一可以有存储空间的地方，对吧
Okay, so that's it, those are the three parts of a protocol.
好的，这就是协议的三个部分了
Now I'm gonna take a little aside, and
现在我先要讲一点别的
not even gonna spend too much time on this, but
并且不会在这上面花费太多时间
all the methods and vars in a protocol are mandatory.
一个协议中的所有方法和变量都是具有强制性的
If you're wanna raise your hand and
如果你要举起手来并
say, I implement this protocol.
说，我要实现这个协议
If you're a struct or enum or a class, you have to implement
如果你是一个结构体、枚举类型、或类，你必须要实现所有的
all of the methods and all the vars in Swift. However,
方法和所有的变量，在 Swift 中是这样的，但是
in Objective-C, that was not true. In Objective-C,
在 Objective-C 中，并不是这样的。 在 Objective-C 中
protocols could have optional methods. Methods or
协议可以有可选方法。协议中的
vars in the protocol that you could choose to implement or
方法或变量你可以选择去实现或者不去实现
not. Now, that's quite a big difference and the way Swift
那么这是与 Swift 的很大的不同，而 Swift 处理它的方式
deals with that is it allows you to put @objc, in front of
是它允许你将 @ojbc 放在
you declaration of a protocol to make it so that this
你的协议的声明的前面，以表示这是一个
is an Objective-C protocol instead of a switch protocol.
Objective-C 协议而不是一个 Swift 协议
And the only difference is that now,
而唯一区别是，现在
methods inside of your protocol can be marked
你协议中的方法可以被标记为
optional. Not optional like you know question mark,
可选的。不是像问号、感叹号那样的可选类型
exclamation point, that kind of optional enum.
那是一种可选的枚举类型
I'm talking about optional like you can optionally
我正讲的是像你可以选择去实现但你不一定要实现
implement the method but you don't have to implement if you
这个方法，如果你
don't want to. Okay, so that's a special kind of backwards
不想去实现的话。好的那么这就是一种特殊的对
compatibility mode to Objective-C, but
Objective-C 的向后兼容
in Swift, we don't do that. So the only time we're ever gonna
但是在 Swift 中，我们不会那样做。所以在这们课中
have this going on in this class is when we're using iOS
我们只有在我们用到了在 Objective-C 中
API that was designed back in the Objective-C world.
设计的 iOS 应用程序接口的时候才会这样做
Specifically, delegation,
具体来讲，是代理（delegation）
which is that blind view to controller communication.
它是那个匿名的视图和控制器的通信
That is all Objective-C style protocols and so
那些都是 Objective-C 风格的协议
when you start using that down the road in the coming weeks,
所以在接下来几周，当你开始去那些东西的时候
you're gonna see these protocols that are marked
你会看到那些协议被标记为
Objective-C and some of them are marked optional
Objective-C 并且有一些被标记为可选的
that you don't have to implement a method.
可选的方法你不必须要去实现
That's not Swift. That's Objective-C compatibility.
那不是 Swift，那是 Objective-C 的兼容性
So just put that in the back of your brain so
所以先把这些记下来
that when you see it, you're like, whoa. I thought I had to
当你看到它时，你就会，哇，我本以为我必须要
implement all the methods in your protocol. Yes, you do in
实现你协议中的所有方法。是的，在 Swift 中你是要的
Swift. Only this exception, all right, back to protocols.
除了这个例外。好的，回到协议
Okay, so how do we declare a protocol? What does the syntax
那么我们应当如何声明一个协议呢？那个语法是什么样的
look like? Well, it looks a lot like declaring a class.
它跟声明一个类很像
Protocol, SomeProtocol, SomeProtocol is the name
protocol SomeProtocol，SomeProtocol 是协议的
of that protocol just like if you say at class whatever
名字，就像 class whatever 中
that would be the name of the class.
whatever 是类的名字
Notice that there's also colon, InheritedProtocol1,
注意这里还有 :InheritedProtocol1, InheritedProtocol2
InheritedProtocol2 actually it can be any number of these.
事实上这里可以有任意数量的这些东西
These are the other protocols that SomeProtocol inherits.
这些是 SomeProtocol 继承的那些协议
Okay, so there is inheritance in protocols. It means
所以说，协议中也是有继承的，这
a little bit different thing then in a class.
与类中的继承有一点不同
Okay, inheritance in the protocol world means,
在协议中的继承的意思是
if you wanna claim to implement SomeProtocol. You
如果你声明要实现 SomeProtocol，你
also have have to implement InheritedProtocol1 and
同时要实现 InheritedProtocol1 和
InheritedProtocol2. So it's almost like it's a mandatory
InheritedProtocol2。所以那差不多就是一些必须的
additional protocols you must implement if you wanna say
额外的协议，你必须要去实现，当你声明要
you implement this protocol. We call that protocol
实现这个协议时。我们称这为协议继承
inheritance. We call it that because some protocol inherits
我们这样叫它是因为一些协议继承了
the requirement to implement these other protocols. Now,
要实现它所继承的那些协议的要求
once you go inside the definition of protocol,
当你进入一个协议的声明
you can see there's no code. Protocols have no code,
你会发现这里没有代码。协议不包含代码
they are not implementations,
它们不是实现
they are purely declarations. And, in fact, when you declare
它们单纯的只是声明。并且事实上当你声明
that you're gonna have a var be part of your protocol,
一个变量将会作为这个协议中的一部分时
all you get to say is whether it's a read-only var,
你只能决定它是一个只读变量
which would be get or
也就是 get ，或者是
a read-and-write var with get set like this.
一个可读可写的变量，也就是 get 和 set，像这个
So this one right here some property would be get and set.
那么这里的东西表示它是这是一个可获取与赋值的属性
So if you wanna implement this protocol, your class or
如果你希望实现这个协议，你的类
struct and you wanna implement this, you would have to have
或者结构体和你想要实现这个，你必须要有一个
a var that can be get and set. Okay, that's what that means.
可以获取与赋值的变量。这就是它的意思
Any methods that you have in your protocol
你协议中的所有可能被结构体实现
that might be implemented by a struct and modified the thing
的方法，如果它会改变那个东西的话
have to be marked mutating of course, right?
当然必须要被标记为可变的（mutating）
Because again Swift needs to know oh
因为 Swift 需要知道，喔
this method might change the thing that implements it.
这个方法可能会改变实现它的那个东西
Now there's a little trick if you want, if you know
如果你想知道的话，这有一个技巧。如果你确定
this protocol's never gonna be implemented by a struct,
这个协议绝不会被一个结构体实现
then you don't need the mutating. But you have to mark
那么你就不需要 mutating。但你必须要去标记
the protocol to say this is a class only protocol. You do
这个协议来表示这是一个只会被类实现的协议
that by saying colon class as the first thing right after
你可以通过将 : class 放在协议声明的后的第一位
the protocol declaration. You see how I put that yellow
你看到我将那个黄色的
colon class up there? Okay, so then if you did that then
: class 放在那了吗？好的如果你这样做了
you would not have to put the mutating because of course,
你自然就不需要放 mutating 在那里了
you never have to put mutating in a class, but
你在类中从不需要 mutating
then this protocol could not be implemented by a struct.
但之后这个协议就不能被结构体实现了
It could only be implemented by a class, we rarely do this.
它只能被类实现，我们很少这样做
Okay we don't usually make a protocol, be restricted to
我们不通常不将一个协议限制为只能
a class and in fact 99% of all the protocols you're gonna see
由类实现，并且实际上 iOS 中 99% 的协议
in iOS could be implemented by anybody. Okay,
可以被任何东西实现
what else we got here. Yes,
这里还有什么，对了
you can an even add an init to your protocol. And that means
你甚至可以在你的协议中加上初始化（init），这意味着
if you're a class or a struct that implements this protocol,
如果一个类或者结构体要来实现这个协议
you have to implement this init.
它必须要实现这个初始化
So, I have to be able to initialize you. So, that
我必须能够初始化这个它
was how we declare a protocol, now let's look how a class or
那就是我们声明一个协议的方法，现在让我们来看看一个类
a struct says, raises his hand and says yes, I will
或者结构体要如何举起手来，说好，我将
implement this protocol. All it does is in a class after
实现这个协议。一个类需要做的只是
the superclass, you just say comma all the protocols you
在它的父类后面，加上逗号和所以他
claim to implement. It's as simple as that, of course, for
声明要实现的协议。就是这样简单，当然
a struct there is no superclass, so
对于结构体来说，它没有父类
you would just say enum or struct, whatever, colon
所以你只用 enum 或 struct whatever（名字）:
the protocols you implement. Okay, so that's how you claim.
再加所以你要实现的协议。好的，那就是你如何声明实现
This is you raising your hand and say I implement that.
这就是你举起手来并说你要实现那协议
As soon as you say that the Swift compiler is gonna check
你一这样说，Swift 的编译器就会去确定
to make sure you actually implement those methods and
你真的实现了在那个协议中的方法和
vars in that protocol. And if you don't, you're going to get
变量。如果你没有，你会得到
errors. It's gonna say you do not implement this on protocol
错误。它会说你没有实现这个协议中的
method whatever. And you're have to go do that, all right?
某个方法什么的。而你必须要去实现它们，对吧
You can do any number of protocols that you want.
你可以实现任意你想要的数量的协议
That's sometimes why we say that protocols can provide
那就是有时我们说协议可以提供
multiple inheritance because you can have as many of these
多重继承，因为你可以放
ah, as you want going on there. Ah, by the way,
任何你想要的数量的协议在那里，还有
if there is an init in the protocol and
如果在协议中有初始化
you're a class and you say, implement that protocol,
而一个类要实现这个这个协议
you have to mark there, your init required.
你必须要在那里标注 required
That's because you wouldn't want a subclass to come along.
那是因为你不想让一个子类跑出来
Subclass you, subclass that init away which is possible.
继承你，并且将那个初始化继承了，这是可能的
It's possible to subclass and make it so
子类可能这样做
an init doesn't work anymore from your superclass.
那么这个继承自父类的初始化就不再有效
You don't want to allow subclasses to do that because
你不希望允许你的子类这样做
then a subclass would no longer implement this protocol
因为如果这样做了，子类不会再实现这个协议
and yet people might think it does because it inherits from
但人们可能会认为它依然实现了协议，因为它继承
something that does. So, once a class implements protocol,
的父类实现了。因此每当一个类实现了协议
all it's subclasses have to as well, so all init would have
它的所有子类必须也要能实现，所以所有的初始化
to be required. Cuz init kind of special,
都要被标为 required，因为初始化有些特殊
in that it's possible in your subclass, to make it so
在你的子类中，是有可能让某些来自父类的初始化
you no longer implement a certain init with certain
不被实现的
arguments. By the way, in your reading, there's a whole bunch
顺带，在你们的阅读作业中，有许多关于
about making inits in classes. It's probably
在类中做初始化的东西，这可能是
the most complicated long part of your reading for this week.
你们这周最复杂的，最长的阅读部分
You gonna have to fight through it cuz it's pretty
你们要坚持下来，因为
complicated. Inheritance makes initialization really
这是挺复杂的，继承让初始化变得非常
difficult because you've got your own vars, you've got your
难，因为你有自己的变量，你有你的
superclasses vars. You've got to get things initialized
父类变量，你要让初始化以
in the right order, all that, it's quite complicated.
正确的顺序进行，之类的东西，那是挺复杂的
So, unfortunately one of the things that you subclass
而很不幸的是，这其中的一件你子类可以做
can make it so you don't implement an init anymore.
的事情就是不去实现一个初始化
So that's why you have to mark it required. One thing
那就是你必须将它标记为 required 的原因
is you don't have to add your conformance to a protocol.
还有就是你不一定要将实现协议的部分
You don't have to add all the methods, and
不一定要将一个协议的方法和
vars in that protocol. In your actual class declaration, or
变量放在你的类声明中
your struct declaration you can add it with an extension,
或者你的结构体的声明中，你可以将他们放在扩展（extension）中
you know how we can extend Int to add arc4random.
你知道我们扩展 Int 并且添加 arc4random 的方法
Well we could extend Int to conform to some protocol.
我们也可以扩展 Int，让他来实现某些协议
Okay, that would be perfectly fine.
这是非常好的
We would just say extension Int :,
我们只用写 extension Int:
the protocol we wanted int to implement and then in there,
加上我们希望 Int 实现的协议
and the extension we would put all the implementations of
并且在扩展中，我们会将所有变量与方法
the vars and methods in that protocol. And
的实现放在那里
this is actually quite common to use an extension just for
这样用扩展是相当普遍的方法
code book keeping. Well sometimes use an extension to implement
为了让代码更有序，用扩展来实现
a whole protocol. It's just nice groups it all nicely.
整个协议。这样可以很好的将它们聚集在一起
Okay, let's see an example of using protocols like
好的，我们来看一个例子，将协议看做
the type they are. Okay, protocols are types. So
类型来使用。协议是类型
let's see, here I have a protocol called Moveable.
看，我这里有一个协议，叫做 Moveable
It has one method in it called, move to, all right?
它其中有一个方法叫做 move(to:)
And I've created a class called Car, which can be moved
并且我创建了一个叫做 Car 的类，车可以被移动
and another class called Shape, like triangle or
和另一个叫做 Shape 的类，像三角形或
square, which can also be moved. Now a Car and
正方形，它也可以被移动。现在一个车
a Shape, incredibly different things and one is class and
和一个形状，完全不同的两个东西，一个是类
one is struct but both of them implement this same protocol.
一个是结构体，但它们都实现了同一个协议
Okay, we're gonna see what it looks like in the code,
我们将会看到在这种情况下
when you have this kind of situation,
的代码看起来是什么样的
which it's perfectly legal to do this. And so
这样做是完全合法的。并且
I've created a couple of vars down at the bottom there,
我在这下面创建了一些变量
a prius, which is a Car, and a square, which is a Shape.
prius 是一个 Car 和一个 square 是一个 Shape
All right, now I'm going to declare a var, thingToMove.
好的，那么我现在要声明一个变量， thingToMove
It's gonna be of type Moveable. Remember I said,
它的类型应该是 Movable，还记得我说过
protocols are types. So I made thingToMove be of type
协议是类型，我将 thingToMove 声明为
Moveable and assigned it to prius, is this allowed?
Moveable 类型，并且将 prius 赋值给它，这样是合法吗
Can I assign prius to the thingToMove? Sure,
我能将 prius 赋值给 thingToMove 吗？当然可以
because a prius implements the Moveable protocol.
因为 prius 实现了 Moveable 协议
It implements that move to over there and it and
它实现了那个 move(to:) 方法并且
it also claims to implement the Moveable. So
它声明实现了 Movable
this is a perfectly legal statement right here, but
所以这个是一个合法的语句
this has made a variable that is not of type Car, or
但这一个不是 Car 类型或类似类型的变量
something like that, it's of type Moveable. So, I can send
它是 Moveable 类型的变量，所以我可以给它
messages like thingToMove.move that's perfectly legal, but
发消息，像 thingToMove.move() 这是完全合法的
I can not say thingToMove.changeOil,
但我不能写 thingToMove.changeOil()
even though a prius is a Car and Car implements changeOil.
尽管 prius 是一个 Car，并且实现了 changeOil()
You see why I can't send that to thingToMove?
你能理解为什么不能向 thingToMove 传递那个信息吗
Because thingToMove is a Moveable. It's not a Car,
因为 thingToMove 是 Moveable 类型，不是 Car 类型
it's a Moveable. So even though the car that happens to
它是一个 Moveable 类型。所以尽管 Car 是
be in that variable, it can do changeOil, I can't send it.
这个变量的一部分，Car 可以 changeOil()，我不能传递它
Swift will not allow me to send that message because
Swift 不允许我传递这个信息，因为
thingToMove in Swift's
在 Swift 的认知中 thingToMove
mind is just a Moveable. The only thing Swift knows
是一个 Moveable 类型，Swift 只知道这一点
that it can do is move to, right?
知道它只能做到 move(to:)
So this is the most important thing on this entire slide,
这是这页幻灯片中最重要的东西
is that red thing. You cannot do changeOil if you have a var
这红色的部分，你不能让 thingToMove 类型变量去
which is of type thingToMove. But what are some things you
changeOil()。但是你能做什么呢
can do? Well, I can say thingToMove equals square.
我可以写 thingToMove = square
Cuz a square is a Shape, and a Shape implements Moveable.
因为 square 是 Shape 型，而 Shape 实现了 Moveable
I could even have an array of Moveable and put a prius and
我甚至可以有一个 Moveable 类型的数组，并将 prius
a square inside of it. Cuz even though a prius and
和 square 放进去。因为尽管 prius 和
square are completely different,
square 是完全不同的
one's a struct, one's a class, one's a Car, one's a Shape.
一个是结构体，另一个是类，一个是 Car，另一个是 Shape
They're completely not really different,
它们不是完全不同的
they can be in the same array, because they're both Moveable,
它们都可以放进同一个数组中，因为他们都是 Moveable 的
you see that? And of course I can have functions that take
能理解吗？当然我也可以有接收 Moveable
Moveables as an argument. Here's slide,
作为参数的函数，这是 slide(slider: Moveable)
which takes a slider, which is a type of Moveable. And
它接收一个 slider，类型是 Moveable
inside I can say slider.move(to: positionToSlideTo),
而在里面我可以写 slider.move(to: positionToSlideTo)
and then I can call slide the prius,
而我可以调用 slide(prius)
slide the square. Perfectly legal to say because those
slide(square)，这是完全合法的，因为
are Moveables. Yeah, question? >> Does that mean that move
它们都是 Moveable 的，请问。 >> 这是否意味着
to function where Car and
在 Car 中的 move(to:)
Shape have to do the exact same thing, or
和在 Shape 中的 move(to:) 必须要做同样的事吗
do they just- >> You mean,
或者.. >>你是问
do the exact same thing like perform the same action? Okay,
像完成同样的行为的那样的同样的事吗？好的
so the question is, does this mean that move to in Car and
那么他的问题是，在 Car 中的 move(to:) 和 Shape
move to in Shape, do they have to do exact same thing?
中的 move(to:) 它们是不是要做同样的事
And the answer is, no. They can do anything they want.
答案是，不是，它们可以做任何它们想的事
They can do whatever move to makes sense for a Car or
它们可以做任何对车看起来有道理的 move(to:)
whatever move to makes sense for
和对形状看起来有道理的 move(to:)
a Shape. >> If you assign it to
>>[学生提问]
squares. And you call move to,
[学生提问]
how does it decide which move to to use?
>> Okay, so
>>好的
the question is if I declare this Movable protocol and
>>他的问题是，如果我声明了这个 Moveable 协议
then I say something are movable.
并且我说某物是 Moveable 的
They are called move to, how does it know which one to use?
并且以它们调用 move(to:)，它怎么知道要使用哪个 move(to:) 方法
Well, because Swift underneath knows which type it is, okay.
那是因为 Swift 知道它是什么类型的
When we say thingToMove.something
当我们写 thingToMove.something
at that level we're the programmer and
在这个层面我们是程序员
Swift is enforcing that it has to be a movable.
并且 Swift 要求这必须是一个 Moveable 类型的
But when it comes to actually executing the code now Swift
但当代码真正在执行的时候 Swift 看了并说
looks and says, oh it's a Car, so I'm gonna use Car's moveTo.
喔，这是一个 Car 类型，那我将用 Car 的 move(to:)
So Swift behind the scenes is doing it.
所以 Swift 在背后是这样做的
But the whole reason that we're typing thingToMove
但我们写 thingToMove 是
to be of type thing to move is cuz we're telling everyone
Moveable 类型，是因为我们希望告诉所有读
who's reading our code, I'm just using this thing as
这段代码的人，我正用这东西作为一个
a Moveable thing. I don't care that it's a car.
Moveable 类型的。我不管他是不是 Car
My code works on anything that's Movable. So
我的代码对所有 Moveable 类型都适用
I'm just communicating to people reading my code and
所以我正与阅读我的代码的人和我自己交流
to myself in all that but Swift under the covers
但 Swift 是
of course knows which move to execute. It is possible by
知道要去执行哪个 move(to:) 的。同时
the way to have functions that take an argument that has to
一个函数可以接受一个实现了
implement multiple protocols. So here the slipAndSlide is
多个协议的参数。那么这里 slipAndSlide
it's function it's argument x. Those things have to implement
是一个函数并且接受参数 x，x 必须要实现
Movable and they have to implement something called
Moveable 并且它也必须要实现另一个叫做
slippery which is not shown on the slide. So now I cannot say
slippery 的协议，这个协议不在我们幻灯片里
slipAndSlide(prius) because while prius is Movable,
所以我现在不能写 slipAndSlide(prius)，尽管 prius
it's not slippery. And so this would not be allowed,
是 Moveable 但它不是 slippery，所以这样是不被允许的
Swift would complain here. But that's how this &. That's how
Swift 在这里会报错。这就是 & 的意思
you make it so it requires multiple protocol conformists.
用它来表示参数需要能实现多个协议
So you're getting a feel for how we use a protocol init by
所以你能理解我们如何使用协议
declaring vars and arguments to functions. So
以声明变量，作为函数的参数等形式
it's only scratching the surface of protocols.
这只是协议的表面的东西
Yeah, question. >> [INAUDIBLE]
请问 >>[学生提问]
The thing to move [INAUDIBLE]
[学生提问]
square. >> Yeah.
>> So when you
[学生提问]
call function [INAUDIBLE] >> Here let me back up to
[学生提问] >> 让我翻回这里
Okay, so what was that?
好你的问题是什么
>> [INAUDIBLE] >> Yeah.
>>[学生提问]
>> [INAUDIBLE]
[学生提问]
>> Yeah, up there.
>>对，在这里
>> So when you call method on
>>[学生提问]
thingToMove. [INAUDIBLE] >> Okay, so he's saying,
[学生提问] >>好的，他是问
look, I set thingToMove to be a prius. Then I call move to,
看，我将 thingToMove 赋值为 prius，接着我调用 move(to:)
which one did it do?
它执行了哪个
Obviously the prius. Then I set thingToMove to be square.
很明显是 prius 的那个，接着我将 thingToMove 赋值为 square
Now if I called move to, it would use the square's one.
现在我再调用 move(to:)，它会执行 square 的那个
So whatever the last thing it was set to, that's what it'll
所以就是他最后被赋值为什么，就会用哪个的
use. Question? >> [INAUDIBLE]
请问 >>[学生提问]
have to take it up here,
[学生提问]
doesn't have to be mutating actually?
Are you allowed to just drop that whenever valid-
[学生提问]
>> Great question,
>> 很好的问题
he's saying up here look in Car, move to, no mutating.
他是问，看这里 Car 的 move(to:)，没有 mutating
See, down here in Shape, we've got mutating. Up here,
再看到 Shape 中的 move(to:)，有 mutating 这上面
we've got no mutating, that's because Car is a class.
我们没有放 mutating，那是因为 Car 是一个类
Class is a reference type, they don't need mutating, so
类是引用类型，它们不需要 mutatitng
it's perfectly fine. Any other questions about this? Okay,
所以这是没问题的。大家还有什么问题吗？好的
excellent. So now let's talk about the uses of protocol.
很棒。那么我们来讲协议的用法
Now we kinda know what protocols are and
现在我们知道协议是什么
how we can put them in our API, how do we use it? Well,
也知道我们如何将它放到我们的应用程序接口，我们要如何使用它
of super important to use is this MVC delegation thing,
这个 MVC 代理是很重要的
right? We've got these generic view things,
我们有泛型视图
like scroll views and table views and things like that.
像滚动视图（scroll view）和表格视图（table view）
And then we've got these very specific controller things,
然后我们还有这些非常具体的控制器
how does a generic thing talk to a specific thing without
在不知到对方是什么时，一个泛型如何
knowing anything about that specific thing?
与一个具体类型通信呢
Because obviously, when scroll view shifts from Apple,
因为，很显然的，滚动视图是由苹果发布的
it knows nothing about Concentration games. So
它对我们的翻牌游戏完全不了解
how do we do that? Well, we use protocols, okay,
所以我们如何做到这一点呢？我们使用协议
so like simple, so this is the will, did, should
这很简单。这就是 will、did、should
and the data at.
和 data at 方法
So let's take a look how we do this, all right? So
那么我们来看看该怎么做
kinda six steps. First a view, like a scroll view or
这有差不多六步。第一，视图，像滚动视图或
table view, it declares it's delegation protocol.
表格视图，它声明它的代理协议
That's just a protocol with a list of all the will, dids and
那就是一个有一系列 will, did, should
shoulds that it wants to send. Remember protocols just a list
那些它希望传递的东西的协议，记得协议只是一个
of methods, right? So it creates that protocol. Then
方法的清单，对吧。那么它创建了这个协议，接着
the view, the scroll view, it creates a var in itself,
视图，像滚动视图，它在自己内部创建一个变量
a public var, it's weak, turns out. And so
一个公开变量，是 weak 型的。所以
it's an optional and that is of type that protocol. Okay,
它是可选类型的，并且这个变量的类型是那个协议
now that's great because now the view whenever it wants
这样很棒，因为现在每当视图想要传递
to send will, did, should, it just sends it to that var.
will, did, should，它只需要传递给那个变量就可以了
And that works because that var is of type that protocol,
因这个变量的类型是那个协议，这是可行的
so of course it can understand all the will, did,
所以当然它可以理解那些 will, did, should
should. Then the controller comes along says, raises its
然后控制器过来并说，举起它的手来
hand and says, I implement that scroll view delegate
说，我实现了滚动视图代理协议
protocol by putting it on this little class line right there.
通过将它放在这个 class 的那一行
And the controller sets itself as that delegate var,
接着控制器将那个代理的变量赋值为自己
it literally says that delegate var equals self.
它实际上就是让那个代理变量等于自己
So it's setting itself as the delegate and that's legal.
所以它让自己成为了那个代理变量，这是合法的
Because the controller has claimed, hey,
因为那个控制器已经声明
I implement that delegate and so, and that delegate is of
我将实现这个代理，并且这个代理的类型是
type that protocol, all is good, okay. And then,
那个协议，一切都很好。接着
of course, the controller has to implement all the methods
控制器当然要去实现这个协议中的
in the protocol. But since this is an Objective-C
所有方法，但因为这是一个 Objective-C 协议
protocol, it actually only has to implement the none optional
它只需要去实现那些非可选的方法
ones. Okay and actually in delegation in iOS,
并且事实上，iOS 中的代理中
almost all the methods are optional. So usually,
几乎所有的方法都是可选的，所以通常来说
you only have to implement the one you really want. But
你只需要实现那些你需要的方法
the controller implements the methods so they did
控制器实现了那些方法
successfully fills out its claim to have implemented it.
因此它成功的完成了声明要去实现协议的任务
And that's it. Now the view is hooked up to the controller.
就是这样。现在视图已与控制器建立了连接
The view can send will, did, and should all it wants.
视图可以任意传递 will, did, should
It has no idea what kind of class is doing it.
它不知道是什么样的类正在处理它
All it knows about, it doesn't even know if it's a class,
它只知道，它甚至都不知道那是不是一个类
could be a struct, it knows nothing about it.
可能是一个结构体，它对此一无所知
All it knows is that that thing implements its protocol,
它只知道那个东西实现了它的协议
so it knows that it can send will, did, and
因此它可以向它传递 will, did, should
should to it through that delegate var. Okay,
通过那个代理变量
make sense? So let's look at the code for
好的，能理解吗？那么让我们以滚动视图为例子来看看
this with the example of a scroll view, okay. Oh, yeah,
实现这个的代码。噢
sorry. Yeah, you find this delegation everywhere in iOS,
抱歉，还有，你会在 iOS 中经常遇到这样的代理
it was designed in Objective-C world. In Swift, we have
它是在 Objective-C 的世界中设计的。在 Swift 中，我们有
closure, which I'm gonna talk about later in this lecture.
闭包，这个我等一下就会讲到
And you could use closures for some of this stuff. But
而你可以用闭包来做这一些事情
even with closures, delegation is pretty cool way to do this,
但是就算是用闭包，代理也是一个完成这件事的很好的方法
have this blind communication. All right, so
通过这样的匿名通信。好的
let's look at the example of UIScrollView. So this is what
让我们来看看 UIScrollView 这个例子，那么这个就是
the var that the scroll view would have in itself.
那个在滚动视图内部的变量
Okay, this is a scroll view var. It's a weak,
这是一个滚动视图中的变量，它是 weak 型的
why is it weak, by the way? Because here the view
为什么它是 weak 型的？因为在这里，这个视图
is gonna have a pointers to the controller, and
会有指向控制器的指针
we know that the controller has a lot of pointers to
并且我们知道控制器有许多指向视图的指针
the view. They'd be keeping themselves in the heap. Okay,
它们被存储在堆中
so what this view is saying here is, I wanna point to
这个视图在这里是说，我想要指向
whoever receives my will, did, and shoulds. But if that will,
接收我的 will, did, should 的东西，但如果
did, and should guy wants to leave the heap,
它想离开堆
that's fine by me, just set this to nil and
我没有意见，只要将这个设为 nil 就好了
I'll stop sending messages to it. Okay, so that way,
而我会停止向它传递信息。好的，通过这样的方式
the view won't keep the controller in the heap.
视图不会导致控制器一直被留在堆里
So anyway, notice this is optional because it's weak.
那么，留心这是一个可选类型因为它是 weak 的
This is the delegate, it's of type UIScrollView delegate.
这是代理，它的类型是 UIScrollViewDelegate
This is what that protocol looks like,
这就是那个协议的样子
it's an Objective-C protocol. It's called UIScrollDelegate,
它是一个 Objective-C 协议，叫做 UIScrollDelegate
and it's got all those funcs in there.
而它有那些函数
ScrollView did scroll to here. Give me the view for
ScrollView 刚刚滚到了这里，给我在这里
zooming over here. It's got about 15 of them in there,
缩放的视图。这大概有15个这样的函数
if you go look at the documentation. So
如果你去看一下文档的话
now the controller comes along, MyViewController,
那么现在控制器过来，MyViewController
and it puts comma, UIViewCont, UIScrollViewDelegate on
并且它的最后有 ,UIScrollViewDelegate
the end and claiming I implement that protocol.
这表示它要实现这个协议
Then, in its probably in its outlet setter,
接着，应该是在它的出口（outlet）设置器
we'll see an example of this today. When that scrollView
我们今天会看这样的例子。当这个滚动视图
gets hooked up on iOS, in the didSet of that,
与 iOS 建立连接后，在它的 didSet 中
it probably says, scrollView.delegate = self.
应该会有这样一段: scrollView.delegate = self
This is a legal statement to say because delegate, which is
这是一个合法的语句，因为代理
this thing up here, is of type UIScrollViewDelegate. And
也就是这个东西，它的类型是 UIScrollViewDelegate 而
MyViewController says over here that it implemented that.
MyViewController 声明它实现了这个协议
So it's legal for it to set itself as the delegate. Okay,
所以它将自己赋值给代理是合法的
and once it does this, they are hooked up, and
它这样做之后，它们就建立了连接
now the view can send will, did, said to the controller
现在视图就可以传递 will, did, should
all at once. Okay, so that's delegation,
给控制器了。好的，这就是代理
probably one of the most obvious uses of protocols.
大概是最明显的协议的用处之一
What's another one? Okay, remember, I talked about that
另一个是什么？还记得我讲过的
key in the dictionary in the hashable business, right?
在字典类型中的键和它的可哈希性吗
So of course, the key in the dictionary has to be hashable.
当然，字典中的键必须是可哈希的
How do we enforce this in our API? Well,
我们如何在我们的应用程序结构中强制做到这点呢
there is a protocol called Hashable.
有一个协议的名字叫做 Hashable
It inherits from another protocol called Equatable, and
它继承了另一个叫做 Equatable 的协议
that's because you know anything about Hashtables.
那是因为，你知道关于哈希表的那些
When you hash something, it's likely to be a unique hash but
当你哈希什么东西是，它很有可能是一个唯一哈希值
it's not gonna guaranteed.
但这不是一定的
You have to follow it up by actually using equals to see
你必须要接着用等于去比较一下
if the two things are actually equal, so we hash in works.
来看是不是有两个东西确实是相等的，这就是哈希的做法
So that's why Hashable inherits from Equatable.
因此 Hashable 是继承 Equatable 的
So if you wanna be Hashable, you also have to be able to
如果你是可哈希的，那么你一定也是可以
check if you're equal to something else. Now this is of
被确定是否与什么相等
super simple protocol, it only has one var in it.
这是一个非常简单的协议，它其中只有一个变量
It's a get only var, which is the hash value.
那是一个只能被获取的变量，这个变量就是哈希值
Some integer, that hopefully, uniquely represents you,
一个整数，幸运的话，能唯一表示你
that's what this is. Now, let's look at Equatable, okay,
这就是它的意思。那么现在我们来看看 Equatable
which, cuz that's another protocol that is inherited and
因为这是另一被继承的协议
thus, required here. What does that look like?
因此它也是需要被实现的，那么看看它是怎样的
That's a very simple protocol as well.
这也是一个非常简单的协议
It has one function in it, one method,
它其中只有一个函数，一个方法
which is static. Meaning it's on the type, like get unique
这是一个静态（static）方法，意味着这是定义在这个类型上的
identifier was in card, remember that? And its name is
就像 card 中的 getUniqueIdentifier，还记得吗
==. In Swift, remember, names of methods can be like emoji.
它的名字是 ==。在 Swift 中，记得名字甚至可以是表情（emoji）
It's not required to be alpha numeric characters, so
它不一定要是字母和数字
they chooses to be called ==, which is kind of cool. And
它被叫做 == 这挺酷的
the arguments are a left-hand side and a right-hand side,
它的参数是 lhs（等号左边）和 rhs（等号右边）
notice that the type is Self, this is a type method, so self
留心它们的类型是 Self，这是一个定义在类型上的函数，因此 Self
is the type. So if this were implemented by int, if int
就是那个类型。因此如果这个协议被 Int 实现，如果 Int
were implementing equitable, self would be int. Okay,
要实现 Equatable，Self 就是 Int
cuz it would be a type function on int, and so
因为这就是一个在 Int 类型上定义的函数
the left-hand side and
所以 lhs 和
the right-hand side would be ints of course. So
rhs 自然就是 Int 类型了
this is basically saying, that your type has to have an ==
所以这就是再说，你的类型中必须有一个 == 方法
method that compares two ints, or whatever you are. And sees
这个方法可以比较两个整数或者其它什么
if they're equal, and returns a bool, yes or no. Okay, now,
并看看它们是否相等，并且返回一个布尔类型，真或者假
this is, that's so that's what you have to do to be Hashable.
这就是如果你想成为可哈希的类型需要满足的条件
But what's really cool, that the == operator in Swift,
但还有一点很酷，在 Swift 中，== 这个操作符
okay, when you say like x == y, that's actually not like
当你使用 x == y 是，那并不是像
built into Swift or anything. All that does is look for
在 Swift 中内置好的，Swift 只是去找
this method, okay. So any two, any class can use,
这个方法。所以任何类都可以使用
can do == as long as you implements this protocol. So
==，只要你实现了这个协议
this protocol is required to make the Hashable work, but
这个协议是 Hashable 的条件，但
it also makes the == operator work. And we're gonna see this
它也可以让 == 这个运算符工作。我们将看到这样的例子
in our concentration demo when I go to implement this. So,
当我在我们的翻牌游戏中去实现它的时候
now that we know that Hashable means you can be a key
现在我们知道可哈希意味着你可以作为一个键
in a dictionary, how is this expressed? Well,
传给字典，但这是如何表达的呢
dictionary which is a generic type, right? It's got these
字典是个泛型（generic type），对吧
two types, the type of the key and the type of the value.
它其中有这两个类型，键的类型和值的类型
It declares itself as Dictionary<Key: Hashable,
字典是这样被声明的 Dictionary
Value>, and that means that key can only work there if
这就说明一个键必须是 Hashable 的
it's Hashable. So this is how we use protocols to constrain
才能被放在那里，这就是我们用协议来限制
these generic types, right? Now Value, right there
这些泛型的。同时 Value
in the dictionary, it doesn't have any colon anything, so
在字典中，它没有 :Anything
Value could be any type.
因此 Value 可以是任何类型
You can put any type whatsoever as the value
你可以吧任何类型放在那当做值
in a dictionary. But the key has to implement hashable. So
但键必须要实现了 Hashable 这个协议
let's go into concentration and do this very thing.
那么我们回到我们的翻牌游戏并实现这个
What do we have in a dictionary? Well, we have one
我们字典中有什么？我们有一个
dictionary, it's that emoji thing. It's, keys are int,
字典，就是表情的那个，它的键是 Int 型
ints are hashable so we're good, and the values
Int 是可哈希的，这是可以的，而值是
are the emoji. And the int is our card.identifier.
那些表情，而 Int 就是我们的 card.identifier
Remember that card identifier? So, I don't want to do that.
还记得我们的 card.identifier 吗，我不想这么做
I want my keys in my emoji dictionary to be cards.
我想在我的表情字典中，键就是牌
I want to look up the cards directly,
我想直接去查找那些牌
I don't want any of that looking at the int thing,
我不想再去找那个整形
that's ridiculous. So, if I go over here to ViewController.
这很没有逻辑，因此我们来到我的 ViewController
Here it is right here, actually.
它在这里
See, here is my emoji thing, int to string, int keys,
看，这就我们的表情的那东西，从 Int 到 String，Int 型的键
string values, this has to be hashable, it is right now.
String 型的值。这里的类型必须要是可哈希的，它现在是的
But I don't want that,
但我不想要它
i just want to look up the cards directly.
我想直接在 cards 中查找
I don't want to use the identifier,
我不想再用这个识别符
I am just going to take this identifier right off of here
我要直接就把这里的 identifier 删去
and when I do this, I'm gonna get errors.
并且当我这样做了之后，我会得到错误
And why am I gonna get errors? Because card, see right here?
而我为什么会得到错误呢？因为 card，看到这了吗
Let's see if we can make this a little wider so
让我看看能不能把它变宽点
you can see it a little better down here.
你可以看得更清楚
It says right here that we cannot subscript,
这里它说我不能...
oh, sorry. Okay, it says cannot subscript a value of
啊抱歉，它说在 [Int:String] 类型变量中
int string with a card. Of course okay,
我们不能用 card 作为下标。当然
I said that the keys were int, and here I'm trying to do it
我这里写的是键的类型应该是 Int，而在这里我正
by card. So I'm just gonna say okay,
试图将 card 型作为键，那么我就说
that I'm gonna have them be cards instead. So I'm just
好啊，那我就把这里改成 Card， 那么
gonna have my dictionary, have keys of card,values of string.
我就让我的字典以 Card 为键，以 String 为值
So now, what do we got here? It says type card
那么现在这个错误是什么呢？它说 Card 这个类型
does not conform to protocol hashable, it worked, okay.
没有遵从 Hashable 这个协议，这生效了！
I tried to make a card be the key of my dictionary and
我尝试让我的 Card 作为我的字典的键
it says, no, card does not conform the protocol hashable.
而它说，不行，Card 没有遵从 Hashable 这个协议
So the declaration dictionary which you can go look up in
字典的声明
the documentation,
你们可以去文档中看
it says card, the key has to be hashable and it wasn't. So
它会说键必须要是可哈希的，而这里的不是
let's go make card be hashable, so
那么我们现在来让我们 Card 成为可哈希的
we won't have this error any more, so
我们就不会再有这个错误了
I'm gonna go over to card, here it is. And here is card,
我们来到 Card，它在这，这是 Card
I'm just gonna say, okay, card is hashable.
我只用写 Card : Hashable
So I just made card hashable, now of course Swift is gonna
我就让 Card 成为可哈希的，当然现在 Swift 会
look at this and say whoa wait a second errors here, card
发现这个然后说，等等，有错误
does not conform to hashable. Card does not conform
Card 没有遵从协议 Hashable。Card 没有遵从协议
to equatable which it doesn't because I don't implement
Equatable，它确实没有，因为我还没有实现
those methods the hash value or the equals equal thing.
那个哈希值和 == 的方法
What's really cool in Swift, look at the fix button here.
Swift 中很酷的东西，看到了这个 Fix 按钮了吗
Do you wanna add protocol stubs? Oh, yes please. And
你想要添加协议的默认实现吗？哦，好的
look what it did. It added a stub for hashable, and
来看看它做了什么，它将 Hashable 和 Equatable 的
a stub for equitables. Now I just have to implement these.
桩代码添加了进来。现在我只需要实现这个
So, making hash value, which has to be get only,
那么，得到 hashValue，这是只能被获取的
that's easy. I'm just gonna return my identifier. That's
这很容易，我只需要返回我的 identifier 那是一个
an extremely good hash for a card because it's unique for
对一张牌来说非常好的哈希值，因为它是唯一确定那张牌的
that card. And the equals equals is also really easy
而那 == 也是非常简单的
too. I just have to compare these two cards.
我只需要比较这两张牌
I'm gonna return if the left hand side's identifier
我只用返回 lhs.identifer == rhs.identifier
equals the right hand side's identifier. So there we go.
就可以了
I've implemented hashable and equatable. So
我已经实现了 Hashable 和 Equatable
now if I go back to my ViewController,
现在如果回到我们的 ViewController
will that error be gone? Here's the error over here.
那个错误会消失吗，那个错误在这里
So let's make Xcode recompile, and sure enough look,
现在我们来让 Xcode 重新编译，看
no problems. It's completely fine with that, okay, and
没有问题。它是完全能接受这个的
that's because I made this hashable. Now,
那是因为，我让这个成为可哈希的了
we can get another benefit of this.
这么做还有一个好处
Let me go back to card. And I told you before, I didn't like
让我们回到 Card，我曾讲过，我不希望
that this identifier was public. I see no reason for
这个 identifier 是公开的，我找不到任何理由
it to be public. And we know we don't need it
让它成为公开的，我们现在在我们的
now to look in our emoji thing, so I'm just gonna make
表情那里也不需要访问它了，所以我将让它成为
it private. And let's see if that's gonna work.
私有的，让我们来看看这能不能生效
So is private gonna work?
它是私有的能生效吗
Let's build and see. Oh, no, we have some errors over here.
让我们组建然后看看，哦不好，我们这有一些错误
So let's go look at them. Here's an error here, it says,
让我们去看看它们，错误在这里，它说
identifier is inaccessible due to private protection level.
identifier 是不可访问的，因为它是私有的
That's right, I made identifier private.
是的，我将它变为了私有的
What's it trying to do here? Oh, here I'm trying to see if
我们这里在尝试做什么？哦，这里我正在尝试去看
two cards match, oh, well cards implement equatable now.
这两张牌是否能配对上，现在 Card 已经实现了 Equatable
So I can just go like this card matchIndex
那么我就只用这样写
=cards[index] because I can compare cards directly,
cards[matchIndex] == cards[index]，因为我现在可以
now. They implement equatable, right?
直接比较牌了，它们实现了 Equatable
Now if we build, that's gone away. So
如果现在我们组建，错误就消失了
we had a huge benefit by making that equatable and
所以让它成为 Equatable 和 Hashable
hashable. We got to use it directly in our emoji thing to
是有很大好处的。我们可以直接在我们的表情里使用它
make that code look nice and look how nice this code looks.
让代码看起来非常的好，看这代码多棒
Compared to how it used to look with that identifier,
相比我们之前用那 identifier
right, so we cleaned up our code on the use side and
所以我们在调用的地方简洁了我们的代码
we were able to go back to card and
并且我们在 Card 中
make something that really didn't need to be public,
让不需要公开的东西私有了
completely private. Pretty cool with that? Okay,
这样挺酷的吧
so you're starting to see the power of protocols a building
你们会渐渐感受到协议在这里是多么的强大
here. So let's go back and look at even more protocol
那么让我们回到这里来看更多酷的
stuff that's cool. All right, there
协议的那些东西。好的，这是
is the demo, okay, let's talk a little about this multiple
那个示例。让我们来讲讲这个多重
inheritance kind of trick. Consider countable range,
继承的技巧，想想可数区间
remember countable range zero dot dot less than something
还记得可数区间就是 0..<Something 这样就会
creates this countable range of ints from zero that thing
创建一个从 0 到 Something - 1 的可数区间
minus one. Countable range implements a lot of protocols.
可数区间实现了非常多的协议
If you go look at countable range, it may have 12 or
如果你去看看可数区间的代码，它大概会有 12
15 different protocols. Well, two of the most interesting
还是 15 个不同的协议。那么其中两个最有趣的的
ones it implements are sequence.
一个是序列（Sequence）
Which makes sense,
这是有道理的
right? A countable range is a sequence of numbers from zero
对吧，一个可数区间一个从 0 开始
to something else. And also collection,
到某个数字的数字序列。还有集合（Collection）
because accountable range is also a collection of things.
因为可数区间是是一个一些东西的集合
If it's accountable range of int,
如果它是一个 Int 型的可数区间
it's a collection of int or whatever. And
那么它就是 Int 型的集合，其他同理
so these two protocols define a lot of fun things like
而这两个协议定义了许多好玩的东西
sequence defines really only one method,
像 Sequence 只定义了一个方法
next, which goes to the next thing in the sequence.
next，到一个序列中的下一个元素的位置
But that let you do for in, anything that implements
但它允许你做 for in，任何实现了
the sequence protocol could do for in, okay, just like
Sequence 这个协议的东西都可以做 for in
anything that's hashable can be a key in the dictionary.
就像任何可哈希的东西可以作为字典的键
And then, collection has even more methods,
接着， Collection 有更多的方法
all the indexing, sub-scripts, all that stuff is all
那些索引，下标，那些东西
in the collection protocol. Now, why do we do this?
都在 Collection 这个协议中，那么为什么我们要这样做？
Why do we have countable range implement all these protocols?
为什么我们有可数区间来实现这些协议
Well, because array implements all those as well, and so
因为数组也实现了它们，同样
does dictionary and set and string. All these classes
字典、集合（Set）和字符串也实现了它们。所以这些类
that are sequences of things or collections of things
它们是一些东西的序列，或者一些东西的集合
implement all these exact same things. And
它们实现了同样的东西
so I as a programmer only have to learn these things once.
所以我作为一个程序员只用学一次这些东西
Okay, I only have to learn learn for in once. And
我只用学 for in 一次
all I need to know is that the thing I wanna for
并且我只需要知道我想对其进行 for in 操作
in over has to be a sequence. So I can just look to see does
的东西，必须是一个序列。所以我可以只去看看
this thing implement that protocol? Or
这东西是否实现了那个协议
I can even invent my own things that I can for in over.
或者我甚至可以创造我自己的类型，我能for in 它
All I have to do is implement the sequencing, the sequence
所有我需要做的只是实现这个 Sequence 协议
protocol which really only has one method in it ultimately.
Sequence 这个协议中只有一个方法
So that's one good reason why because I learned indexing,
这很好的解释了为什么我学了索引
indexOf to get things and I can now do indexOf
indexOf 来获得一些东西，那么现在就可以 indexOf
on a string and find a character on a string or
一个字符串并找到一个字符，或
I can do indexOf in an array and find in there.
我可以 indexOf 一个数组并在其中查找
I can even do indexOf on accountable range not super
我甚至可以 indexOf 一个可数区间
valuable but if the count of a range wasn't of int,
这不是很有用，但如果这个可数区间不是 Int 型的
then it might be interesting to do index of to try and
这可能也会很有趣，去 indexOf
find something where it is in the range, okay. But
并在这个区间中找到某物在哪
there's a bigger and better reason why we do this.
但我们这么做还有个更重要的原因
And that's because there's a little bit of magic in, or not
那是因为在 Swift 中，有一点小魔法，或者说
magic but really good design implementation in Swift.
不是魔法，但是非常好的设计实现
Which is that for protocols it is possible to provide default
对于协议来说，协议是可以提供默认
implementations of methods. Default implementations
的方法的实现的。默认的方法
of methods. So this makes it possible for
实现，这让我们有可能
us to implement indexOf for
来为这些所有的类实现
all of these classes in one place. So that's why,
indexOf，在一个地方，这就是为什么
again, we think it's like multiple inheritance cuz
我们认为它像多重继承
they're actually gonna inherit implementation. So where do
因为它们实际上是会继承实现的。那么我们将
you put this implementation? Cuz we know protocol is just
这样的实现放在哪里呢？因为我们知道协议只是
a declaration method with no implementation. Well,
方法的声明，而不包含实现
the answer is you put them in an extension to your protocol.
答案是，将它们放在你的协议的扩展中
You know how we can have extension int? You can also do
你知道我们是如何为 Int 添加扩展的。你也可以
extension protocol. And in that extension you can
为协议添加扩展。并在这个扩展中，你可以
implement as many other protocol methods as you want.
实现任意数量的协议中的方法
Now you're little bit restricted there because
不过你在这里有些受限，因为
extensions can't have any storage.
扩展不能有任何的存储
We know that, right? No vars, so that's certainly
我们知道这点，没有变量，那肯定是一个限制
a restriction. Also in the extension, really the only
并且，在扩展中
method you could use to implement it are the methods
你能用的方法只能是
in the protocol or in the protocols you inherit.
在这个协议中的方法，或者是这个协议继承的协议中的方法
So, like collection, happens to inherit from sequence so
就像 Collection，它是继承了 Sequence 的
a lot of the collection methods can be implemented
因此很多的 Collection 的方法，都可以用
using the sequence by just going through the whole
Sequence 实现，通过遍历整个
sequence of the collection and finding things, or whatever.
集合的序列，找到一些东西，或其他什么
So if you look here, sequence has that one important method
如果你看看这里，Sequence 有那个重要的方法
next goes to the next thing in the sequence. But
next，它可以去到这个序列中的下一个元素，但
sequence also has all these other methods,
序列也有其他的这些方法
contains which finds whether somethings in the sequence,
contains 用来确认序列中是否包含某个元素
forEach which kind of does what for n does. Joined by
forEach 差不多就是 for in 的功能。 joined by
separator, which takes all the things in the sequence,
separator 用来获取序列中的所有元素，并
converts it to a string and creates a big string
转换成一个字符串，它会创建一个大字符串
joined by a separator like comma or space. It has min,
这个字符串被 separator 分割，像逗号或者空格
find me the minimum thing in this sequence, max,
它还有 min 用来找到序列中的最小元素
the maximum thing. Even has functions that take closures,
max 找到最大元素。甚至还有函数接收闭包为参数
which I'm going to talk about soon like filter and
闭包我等一下就会讲到，像 filter 和 map
map, that do major operations on the sequence.
它们可以对序列做一些主要操作
Well, all the implementation of all those things contains,
所有的这些东西的实现，contains
forEach, joined, min, max all those things.
forEach, joined, min, max 所有这些东西
Those are all implemented in an extension to sequence that
它们都在 Sequence 这个协议的扩展中被实现了
Apple provides so that if you want to have a sequence,
这是苹果提供的扩展。因此如果你想要有一个序列
as long as you implement that next thing to go to the next
你只需要实现那个 next 方法，它可以去到
thing in the sequence you get implementations of all those
序列中下个元素，实现了它，你就可以得到整个
other things for free. That also means that array, and set
Sequence 协议的实现，这也意味着数组，集合
and dictionary, and countable range are all sharing
字典和可数区间都在共享 min, max 这些
the implementations of min and max and all these things.
方法的实现
Now, these are only default implementations.
这些只是默认实现
If an array you actually implement min or max or
如果一个数组真的去实现了 min 或者 max
something like that. Maybe you can do it more efficiently
或者其他的方法，也许你可以比默认实现
than the default implementation or
做得更有效率或者
whatever. You can do it. But it's replace the default
其他什么，你可以这样去做，但这样会替代扩展中的
implementation that's in the extension.
默认实现
Okay, but are you getting the feel for what I'm saying?
你能理解我在讲的是什么吗
Why this is valuable to have these default implementations.
为什么默认实现很有价值
You can have these really powerful protocols and
你可以有这些非常强大的协议
you'll only have to implement one of the methods and
而你只要实现其中一个方法
you'll get implementations for
你就可以得到整个的实现
all of them. And then they're shared across all these weird
而它们被这些奇怪的
different classes like array, string,
不同的类共享，像数组，字符串
countable range. They all get all these implementations they
可数区间，它们的可以获得这些实现
don't have to implement any of that and they get it for free.
而自己本身不用去实现什么，免费地获得了这些实现
Now all of these that I'm talking about generics,
那么所以这些我讲的，泛型
value typing, var versus let immutability
数值类型，变量与常量控制
control, constraining things by protocols, extensions or
通过协议来限制，扩展
protocols. All these things add up to support a kind of
还有协议，所有的这些东西共同支撑着一种编程模式
programming called functional programming. How many people
叫做函数式编程，这有多少人听说过
here have heard about functional programming?
函数式编程
About half of you, see? So
大概一半左右
I encourage you at your Stanford careers,
我推荐你在你斯坦福大学的学习中
go take a class and learn about functional programming.
去上节关于函数式编程的课程
It's really kind of the evolution, some would say,
有人会是它是面向对象编程的
of object-oriented programming. It's a little
一个进化
different way of thinking about dividing things up.
它在如何将事物分开有不同的想法
It allows you to get things like multiple inheritance
它允许你使用多重继承
without things getting completely out of control.
而不会让事情变得完全超出掌控
Since things aren't living in the heap,
因为那些东西不是在堆中
you don't have 20 pointers to something and you're not sure
你不会有像20个指针指向某个东西
who's gonna modify things, so your programs are much more
而你不确定哪个指针会改变这东西，所以你的程序会变得更加
provable, right? You can prove that they do what they do.
可证明，你可以证明它们会做它们应该做的事情
You don't have to worry about what pointers are messing this
你不需要担心哪个指针会把堆中
thing up in the heap lot of advantages of it. Now,
的哪一个东西搞砸。这有很大的优势
what's really cool about Swift,
而 Swift 很酷的一点是
it supports both these programming models.
这两个编程方法它都支持
Object oriented programming, which is all I'm gonna
面向对象编程，这个我将会在
use in this class because that's the prerequisite for
这整门课中讲到，因为这是参加这门课的前提
this class, and functional programming,
还有函数式编程
which is what pretty much all of the foundation of
这差不多就是那些基础框架框架，像字典、数组
foundation framework like dictionary, array, string,
字符串这些东西的基础
all those things. Those are all built with a functional
它们都是以函数式编程
programming model. Swift supports them both equally,
模型建立的，Swift 两个都支持
which is really great. So it's kind of your best,
这很好。这是可以说是最好的
it's a mix between languages like Haskell,
它可以说是 Haskell 和 Java 的结合
how many of you have ever heard of the language Haskell?
有多少人听说过 Haskell 这门语言
Okay, same people who know about functional programming,
好的，同样是听说过函数式编程的那些人
right, so Haskell which is a purely functional programming
Haskell 是纯粹的函数式编程语言
language, and you know, like Java which is a purely object
而 Java 是纯粹的面向对象
oriented language. It's a good mix of two. That's all I'm
编程语言，而 Swift 是它们两的结合
going to say about functional programming, just so
这是我关于函数式编程所有要讲的部分
that you know it's there. That's it for protocols.
只是为了让你们知道有这个东西，协议我们就讲到这里
When you see it all in action it will make a lot more sense.
当你在实战中遇到它，你就能理解了
Hopefully it makes a lot of sense.
希望你就能理解了
Now it's really, protocols are very simple.
协议非常的简单
Just those lists but we can use them in powerful ways,
就是那些清单，但我们可以将它用作非常强大的途径
all right. Now let's go talk for briefly about something
好的，那么现在我们来简要的讲讲
that's not super important, but strings are in almost
一个不是那么重要的东西，字符串，字符串在每个
every app. And I just wanna talk a little bit about how we
应用程序都存在，而我只想讲讲关于
index in to strings, cuz it is not what you would
我们如何索引字符串，因为这不会像你们第一眼
think it is at first glance. In addition to string,
看到所想的那样，除了字符串
the struct string, there's another struct in foundation
结构体字符串，在 Foundation 中有另外一个
called character. Now, a character is what we humans
叫做 Character 的结构体，一个 Character 就是
would perceive of as a character. On the screen or
我们所看到的一个字符，在屏幕上
whatever. However, a string is not a sequence. A string is
或是其他什么东西上。但是，一个字符串并不是一个序列
an underlying built with character, it's built with
字符串是以字符为基础建立的
unicodes. Okay, unicodes are just little bite size chunks
它是以 Unicode 为基础建立的，Unicode 就是那几个字节
that can represent pretty much any language on earth. Okay,
的数据，而它可以表示基本上地球上的所有语言
it's international. You know, like ASCII.
它是国际化的，像 ASCII
We used to have ASCII, you can only really do English.
我们以前用 ASCII，它只能表达英语
Unicodes do all All the languages on Earth.
Unicode 可以表示地球上的所有语言
So that's what's in a string. So we have a little bit
这就是字符串中的东西，我们就好像正在
of trying to bridge the world between Unicodes and
尝试在Unicode 的世界与 Character 的世界
characters. So let me show you by example here,
搭建桥梁，让我为你们展示一个例子
if we have the word cafe, C-A-F-E, right?
如果我们有 cafe 对吧
That we perceive to have four characters, the C, the A,
那么我认为它由 4 个字符组成，c、a
the F, and the E with the accent on it. But
f、e 其中 e 的上方有重音符号
it might be represented by five Unicodes, because there's
但是它可能是被 5 个 Unicode 字符表示的
a Unicode which is put an accent on the previous
以为有一个 Unicode 的字符是在前一个字符上加上重音符号
character, okay, so, it could have five Unicodes. Well, So
所以它可能会有 5 个 Unicode 字符
how do we deal with this? Well, the main problem or
那么我们如何处理这个呢？那么现在
the main ramification of this is that string
的主要问题是，字符串
cannot indexed by int. Because if we had a phrase,
不可以通过 Int 类型来索引，因为如果我们有一个词组
cafe pesto, right there. One of my favorite pizza joints in
cafe pesto，我喜欢的一个比萨店
Hawaii, Cafe Pesto. The p is that in index 5 or
cafe pesto，p 这个字母的索引应该是 5
is that in index 6? It depends on whether that e is
还是 6，这取决于 e
an e with an accent or two Unicode here there's the e and
是 e 和重音符号组成的一个字符，还是两个字符，分别是
the accent. So ugh, what are we gonna do here? So
e 和那个重音符号。那么我们这里该怎么做呢
what we do is we don't index strings by int.
我们做法是，不允许使用 Int 来索引字符串
Instead strings are indexed by their own special type,
字符串是用一个特殊的类型来索引的
String.Index. And that's the only way
String.Index 并且这是对字符串使用
to use subscripting on a String,
下标的唯一方法
you need a String.Index, not an Int. So this makes this,
你需要一个 String.Index，而不是 Int。那么这就会
people don't like this. They wanna index Strings by Int and
让人们不太喜欢这样。人们喜欢用 Int 来索引字符串
I understand why, but you can't do that. So
我也能理解原因，但你不能这么做
what does that mean? Well, we have to get an index, so
那么这意味着什么呢，这意味着我们必须要获得一个索引
how do we get an index? Well, you can get the startIndex
我们如何获得一个索引呢？你可以得到你个字符串的
of a string, you can get the endIndex of a string.
startIndex（开始索引） 和它的 endIndex（结束索引）
You can also use index(of:) a character to find the first
你可以用 index(of:) 一个字符来找到这个字符
index of that character. So there's a bunch of different
的第一个索引。所以这样许多不同的方法
methods and vars on strings to get an index.
和变量来让我们获得一个索引
Once you have an index in your hand, now you can offset
一旦你手头有了一个索引，你就可以用 Int 移动（offset）
that index by an Int. So if you want to get the fourth
那个索引。所以如果你想要的到这个字符串的第四个
character in the string you have to get the startIndex and
字符，你必须要得到它的 startIndex
then offset it by three to get to the fourth index, from
并用 3 offset 它这样就能获得第四个下标
the first to the fourth. So it was let's get to the code that
从第一个到第四个，然我们来看看这样的代码
makes that work. So here's my pizzaJoint cafe pesto here,
这是我的 pizzaJoint = "cafe pesto"
I'm gonna get the index of the first character by saying
我将通过使用 pizzaJoint.startIndex
pizzaJoint.startIndex that's not an Int.
的方式来得到第一个索引，而它不是 Int 型
It's of type String.Index.
它是 String.Index
Now I'm gonna get the fourth character by taking
而我通过得到第一个字符的索引
the first character and offsetting it by three.
并 offset 它 3 就可以得到第四个字符的索引
Now I've got the index of the fourth character.
那么现在我有了第四个字符的索引
Now I'm gonna get the actual fourth character by using
那么我就可以通过下标的方式
subscripting. PizzaJoint, subscript, fourth character,
pizzaJoint[fourthCharacterIndex] 这样
index, fourth character index of subtype String.index,
fourthCharacterIndex 的类型是 String.Index
not of type int. And I can also do index (of:), so
而不是 Int。而我也可以用 index(of:)
here I'm gonna say The firstSpace character in
那么我这里要得到第一个空格的位置可以这样写：
cafe pesto is pizzaJoint.index(of: " ").
firstSpace = pizzaJoint.index(of:" ")
Now the reason I have to say if let there is,
我之所以要使用 if let
of course, index(of: " ") could return nil.
是因为，index(of:" ") 当然可能返回 nil
There might not be any spaces in pizzaJoint.
pizzaJoint 中可能根本没有空格
There happens to be but there might not be.
这里碰巧有，但是可能没有的
So it would return nil then. And so I'm doing if let Now,
所以它可能返回 nil 也因此我在这里用了 if let
I've got the index of that space.
现在我有了那个空格的索引
Now I'm going to get the index to the start of the second
现在我想得到第二个单词的开始的索引
word, the word pesto there. And
也就是 pesto 这个单词
we do it by indexing that first space over by one.
我们通过 index（注：这里应该是 offset） firstSpace 1
And I am gonna assume there is one space in between words,
为了能找到下一个单词，我在这里
go to the next one. And now, I am going to get the whole word
假定了单词之间是有空格的。而现在我将要得到整个 pesto
pesto by indexing string with a range, okay. The index
这个单词，通过用区间的方法来所以这个字符串
of a string doesn't have to be an individual index.
字符串的所以不一定要是一个独立的索引
It could be a range of indexes. Now you notice to
他可以是一个由索引构成的区间
make a range, I'm using exactly the same dot,
注意到这里要创建一个区间，我是用的是之前
dot, less than thing that I did when I made that countable
在我们创建 Int 型的可数区间用过的 ..< 的方法
range of INTs. Ranges are generic types. They don't have
区间是泛型，它们不一定要是
to be of INTs. They can be a range of string.index.
Int， 它可以是一个由 String.Index 构成的区间
Perfectly legal. As though we saw before, we had a range,
这是完全合法的，就像我们曾经见过的
countable range, of double precision floating points.
我们有一个由双精度浮点型组成的可数区间
Remember that at the beginning of the last lecture? So
记得在我们上节课的开始讲的那样吗
range is generic type. So
区间是泛型
it is perfectly legal to use a range inside subscripting, and
在下标中使用区间是完全合法的
that's true anywhere there's subscripting of collections.
并且在任何下标是集合的地方都是正确的
These methods, by the way, these index,
这些方法，index()
offsetBy, those are not methods in string,
offsetBy() 这些不是字符串中的方法
those are methods in collection. Okay,
这些是集合中的方法
the collection protocol, string may or
在 Collection 这个协议中的方法，String 可以
may not implement it itself, it's up to the string.
选择去实现或不实现它，这由 String 来决定
The collection protocol is also generic, and so the index
Collection 这个协议也是泛型的，因此在
you use in the collection is configurable. For
Collection 中使用的索引是可配置的
a string it's a string.index. By the way, another way
对字符串来说那是 String.Index。另外一种
to get the second word, and probably what we would use, is
获得第二个单词的方式，我们也可能这样做，是
a more complicated method like component separated by. So
一个更复杂的方法， components(separatedBy:)
components separated by, is a collection method. You give it
它是一个集合中的方法，你像它传递一个
an element that would be in that collection and
会在这个集合中的元素
it will create an array with all the things,
而它会创建一个数组来装所有东西
all the elements in an array grouped and
数组中的所有元素都会被那个东西
separated by that thing. So this would give you an array
分割，这样做就会得到一个由空格分割的
of all the words separated by a space. Then I would grab
单词组成的数组
index one, which would be the second word. Okay,
接着我使用 [1]，这就是第二个单词了
so I'm showing you how to do the indexing directly, but
我给你们讲了如何直接使用索引
a lot of times we use much higher level
但更多时候我们都会用更加高级的
things in string. Okay, so string,
字符串中的东西，那么一个字符串
like I say, is a collection of character. Just like an array
就像我说的，是一些字符的集合，就像数组是一个
is a collection of arbitrary things,
随意某些东西的集合
accountable range of int is a collection of ints, and so
Int 类型的可数区间是 Int 类型的集合
all that stuff is coming from collection. And collection is
那些东西都是来自 Collection 这个协议
a sequence we know, so of course you can do for
而正如我们知道的，Collection 又是一个序列
c and if s is a string c will be a tight character and you
所以你当然可以用 for c in s，当 s 是字符串时，c 是字符
can iterate with a four loop through all the characters.
那你就可以用一个 for 循环来遍历所有的字符
There's also really cool initializer for array
同时数组也有一个非常酷的初始化方法
that takes a sequence, as the argument. So you can say,
它接收一个序列作为参数，那么你就可以写 Array(s)
array of any sequence and what it will do is go through that
s 是序列，这样就会遍历这整个
sequence and take each element and put it into the array.
序列，并将它的每个元素放入这个字符串中
So it creates a big array for you,
这将为你创建一个大数组
cuz it's an array initializer. And
因为这是一个数组初始化方法
in the array will be all the elements of the sequence. So
并且在这个数组是由这个序列的所有的元素组成
since a string is a sequence of characters, if you say
既然字符串是字符的序列
array of string, you'll get an array of its characters. And
如果你使用 Array(SomeString) 你就会得到由它所有字符组成的数组
now you can use int to index them if you want. So sometimes
现在如果你想要，你就可以使用 Int 来索引这个数组了
people, they get tired of all this string index stuff.
有时人们被这个 String.Index 弄得很烦
They just create an array of the characters. And
他们就创建一个由字符组成的数组
then now they can use ints to get at the various characters.
这样他们就可以使用 Int 来索引这个数组并获得许多字符
That's kind of a trick as well.
这也能算是一个技巧
Ah, remember that a string is a value type, it's a struct,
记得 String 是数值类型，它是一个类
we almost always use immutable strings like let s equal
我们几乎一只会用不可改变的字符串像 let s = something
something, we're working with it immutably,
我们就在不可改变地处理它
but of course there are mutable versions, mutable
但当然也有可改变的版本，可改变的
methods. There's another kind of protocol called range
方法，这有另一个叫做 RangeReplaceableCollection
replaceable collection. That's kind of a collections that
的协议，它就是一些可变的东西的集合
can be mutated. Ranges of the things can be replaced. And so
那些可以被替代的东西的区间
here's a method in that insert the contents of
那么这里就有一个方法，可以插入 contentsOf
a collection of characters, which string is, at an index,
一个字符的集合，比如说 String，at 一个索引
so in this case it's index of space,
在这里是 index(of:" ")
that's gotta be a string.index right there.
这里必须是一个 String.Index 类型
And so I can insert the word foo into Cafe Pesto. So
那么我就可以将 foo 这个单词插入 cafe pesto
you can do this, we don't do this that much.
你可以这么做，但我们不经常这么做
We tend to just use them immutably, and we use plus to
我们倾向于就不可变地使用它们，而我们用 + 来将他们
add them together and stuff like that. So that's string,
合并，和其他类似的操作。这就是字符串
it's that little weirdness about the indexing.
它在索引的方面有一点奇怪
Now, There are lots of other methods in string, I want to
字符串中有许多其他的方法
show you an interesting thing about one of them.
我想想你展示其中一个有趣的
So here is replace range, which, my pointer doesn't work
这是 replaceSubrange。啊我的控制器用不了了
any more, but if you look at replace range,
但你看一下 replaceSubrange 那里
do you see where it's red, right there? That's that dot,
看到红色的这个吗？那个
dot less than thing, look, I forgot to put something on
点点小于富豪，我是不是忘了放点东西
the left. So what does that range go from? Okay,
在左边？那这个区间是从哪里开始的呢？
we know it goes to s.endIndex. Well, Swift is smart enough to
但我们知道它是在 s.endIndex 结束。其实 Swift 很聪明
know that that is a range of str-, the strings indexes,
知道这是这个字符串的索引
so it will automatically put start index at the beginning.
所以它会自动认为开始的索引是在字符串的开头
And if you left off the other side,
如果你是只省略右边的话
it will automatically put ending index at the end. So
它会自动把字符串的结尾当作结束的索引
you can oh, leave those arranged things open ended.
也就是，你可以省略其中一个的边界
But Swift has to be able to infer the type of whats going
但 Swift 得先要能够判断发生了什么
on there. So you can't always do it,
所以你并不总是这样做
but in that case you could. Okay, so
但这里你是可以的。好
that's string. I guess we'll go like this. So, to
这就是字符串，就讲到这里。
make this all understandable let's go back to our,
为了让这个更容易理解，我们回到我们的
um, concentration. And we're gonna make this
Concentration 里，我们要把这个
thing right here, this emoji choices,
这里这个 emojiChoices
which is currently an array of emoji strings.
它现在是一个表情字符串的数组
I'm gonna change that. I'm gonna copy and paste it here.
我要把它改掉，我复制粘贴一下
I'm gonna change it from being an array, to being a string.
我把它从数组改为字符串
So I'm gonna take off the array things.
所以我把数组的这些先去掉
And I'm gonna get rid of all of these little commas. And
我去掉这些逗号
now emojiChoices is gonna be a string.
现在 emojiChoices 就是个字符串了
And I'm gonna have my code be the same,
我就保持代码不变
but instead of grab it out of the array, it's gonna grab it
但不从数组里取值了。我获得这些值
out of the string. Now as soon as I change that to a string,
改成从字符串里。现在我把它改成字符串之后
look what happens. Cannot convert value of type
你看会发生什么？不能转换类型为 Int 的值
int to expected argument, string.index. Okay, remove at,
为期待的参数类型 String.Index。好吧，remove(at:)
right here, which we moved to remove the thing,
就这个，我们用来移除表情的
where do you think that's declared? Anyone wanna guess?
你认为这个方法是在哪里定义的？有谁想猜一下吗？
Is that an array thing? A string? No,
那是 Array 类的吗？还是 String 的？不
that's in collection, range replaceable collection, right?
它是 RangeReplaceableCollection 实现的
So it's in a protocol somewhere that both string and
是在这个 protocol 里某个地方，而且 String
array implement. So
和 Array 的遵守了这个协议。所以
you would think it should just work here,
你会认为这个应该可以直接行得通
because emoji choices, yeah, now it's a string, but remove
因为 emojiChoices 只不过现在变成了字符串，即使
at is in range replaceable collection, they're range
remove(at:) 是 RangeReplaceableCollection 里定义的
replaceable collection. Why does this work? Well,
但它们也都遵守这个协议，为什么这个行不通？
because strings are not indexed by ints. And
因为字符串不是靠 Int 索引的
so this doesn't work. So we have to create a string.index,
所以这个不能用。我们必须构造一个 String.Index
I'm gonna do that. I'm gonna create a random string index
那我就这样做，创建一个随机的字符串索引
and I'm gonna do it by using that index offset by things.
I'm gonna say, emojiChoices give me an index, I'm gonna
use this first one right here, index offsetBy, which let's us
take a known index and offset it by something else.
The known index I'm going to start with is the start index
of this thing, so, emojiChoices.startIndex, and
I'm gonna offset by a random int. So that offset,
that can be by an int. That happens to be because
this particular collections strides, or the distance
between indexes is an int. Even though the indexes
themselves are string dot index. So I do that.
So now I'm gonna put random string index in here and
all should be well, right? Because remove at,
oh no, still doesn't work. What's this error?
Cannot assign value of type character to string.
Okay, this is a dictionary, this is looking for
strings. Okay? Why is this a character? Well,
because a string is a collection of character. So
if remove at, I'm removing a character. So no problem here,
we know that we can probably convert types. And
we're gonna do that by using a string initializer that
takes a character as an argument and
returns a string with just that character in it. So now
we converted it. So, that's it. That's all we need to do.
And I did this just so you can see all that offsetBy, and
all that stuff so you could see how we would index this
into a string instead of doing here. So, hopefully
this is still working. Yes, it is. It's still working.
Okay? Got it everybody? Questions about this? So
this is the important line of coding in here. And
also a little bit of understanding that even though
remove at is in collection range, replaceable collection,
the types matter, because it's a generic type.
Collection is a generically typed protocol. All right,
let's go back. Oops, not there. Here, no. Here.
All right, let's talk about another class that has
to do with Strings which is NSAttributedString. For
NSAttributedString is a String that every character
has a little dictionary associated with it. And
that Dictionary can have lots of little keys and
values that say how to draw that character on screen.
Okay so those Dictionaries can have things like font, color,
all these things. Okay that's what an attributed string is,
right? A String with attributes of each character,
right? The Dictionary that each character can have.
The keys are well known,
you can look them up in the documentation.
The values depend on the type of thing, so
sometimes the values are UI font, which is a font thing,
sometimes the values are colors,
sometimes they're floating point numbers, etcetera.
Now a lot of times, we use the same Dictionary for big long
ranges of characters, right? You know like if users select
some text on screen and they say make it orange, then we're
gonna have one Dictionary for all those characters so not
like every character has to have a different Dictionary.
And in your homework,
the entire String is going to have one Dictionary. So
I've given you a really easy use of attributed String and
you're gonna see why I did that in a moment here.
Once you have an Attributed String with all those font and
color for each character,
now you can use to it to set the text in UI label, or
to set the title of a UIButton. Or next week we're
going to learn how to draw it directly on-screen, in our own
drawing classes. Okay? Here's how you create and
use an AttributedString, and it's got red.
Any time you see red on my slides, it's kind of like oh,
look out. And this is red because it's really weird.
Okay? And why is this really weird? Well, it's really weird
cuz this is an Objective-C API that's trying to live
in the Swift world, and that requires a little bit of
compromise. There's not a lot of APIs like this.
Every time iOS comes out, the next one I always hope there
can have Non NSAttributedString, just
regular AttributedString would now fix this, but they haven't
done it yet. So, when you're declaring those attributes,
the little Dictionary that goes on each character,
you have to give it an explicit type.
You cannot let the type be inferred and
that's because those values could be font,
colors, whatever. So, a source can't infer what the value of
the Dictionary is. So they type that you're gonna use
here is Keys are NSAttributedString key.
And you can just look that up in the documentation,
see what the choices are. It's things like font, underline,
strike through, all the things you would think to be.
And then the value is Any. Okay, so
Any is a special Swift thing that means
anything can go here, any struct, any class, any type.
So this is very non Swift cuz Swift is strongly
typed, and here's there's no type. So
you would never have an API like this in Swift. Okay,
if this weren't an Objective-C API brought forward, so
you would never have it.
Can anyone think of what we would have instead of
any right there? Why type of thing instead of any?
How about an enum with associated values? Right?
If you had an enum, and one of the enum things is the font,
then the associated value could be a font.
Or what if the thing was the color of the text?
Then the associated value could
be a UI color, you see? How we would do that in Swift? Well,
we didn't have those enums when Objective-C did this so,
we're stuck with Any. Okay?
Never use any in your data structures. Any is purely so
we can deal with these old Objective-C things. Alright,
so, now that I have declared the type to be a dictionary
with NSAttributeString keys with Any as the value, then I
can make my dictionary and so StrokeColor is obviously
the color that it strokes the outside of the text.
There's also foreground color which is the color it puts
the inside of the text, the fill color. There's also
background color which is like if you had a highlighter,
that's the background of it. There's also StrokeWidth.
StrokeWidth, if it's a positive number,
it outlines. Okay? If it's a negative number its solid.
The character is solid. Okay? You'll see that. We're going
to do a demo of that. Okay? So you can do this. You can put
these things in here for your homework. You'll use stroke,
color stroke with maybe a couple others. In the hints I
kind of tell you the things you need to use.
So, I don't want you wasting too much time looking up all
these things. Then you can created an attributed string
with that Dictionary for all the cards in the string by
just saying NSAttributedString using the initialize of
the text of string and the attributes. So that creates
an attributed string then I can take that attributed
string and like put it on my flipCountLabel, right?
Now my flipCountLabel, so this particular ones since I'm
using a positive stroke width this would be outlined text.
On my flip count. So I'm gonna do a demo and
see what that looks like in a second here.
I just briefly want to talk about the peculiarities of
NSAttributed strings since there's an NS.
You know, you see that NS at the beginning and you know,
hmm, this is kinda of an older API.
It's not a String. It's a totally different thing, okay.
An NSAttributedString is a class that's completely
different. Then String worked completely differently.
Because it's a class not a struct,
you can't make a mutable one by just using var.
You actually have to use a different class.
And it's mutable Attributable String. If you actually
wanted to go set the dictionaries on certain
characters individually, you would need to use a mutable
Attributable String, a completely different class
there. Also NSAttributedString was built and
constructed internally with NSString in mind. NSString is
the old Objective-C String. NSString and String have
a little different Unicode and coding underneath. So,
when you have wacky characters like emoji or cafe in there,
the indexes into them might not quite match up. And
there's automatic bridging between string and NSString so
if you have any iOS API that takes an NSString
as an argument, you can just pass a string.
It just automatically works except,
that this little encoding doesn't always get
fixed up quite right so the bottom line here is if you're
going to be trying to be index into an NSAttibutedString and
you have wacky characters like emoji or cafe, the indexes
might not line up very well. Now in your homework you don't
have to worry about any of that cuz I'm only gonna ask
you to make the entire String have the attributes. So
you're not even doing any indexing into there.
But in the future, if you're ever using AttributedString,
just be careful about
the indexing in there if you've got wacky characters.
All right, the demo. So, I'm gonna do this flip count
thing and show you what this looks like real quick here.
Where do we do that? That's right up here,
right? Here's where we set our flipCountLabel to Flips:
\(flipCount). So I'm going to put attributed text there. So
I'm going to let my attributes, which I have to
type to be [NSAttributedStringKey:
Any] =. And now I can just put the things I want, so
I want the StrokeWidth to be 5.0.
Okay, that's a fairly thick stroking width.
And then what was the other thing I said I wanted to, oh,
the color. So the strokeColor and I'll go ahead and
use the color literal here. Use our favorite color,
which is orange. Halloween color. Okay,
so now if I wanna use these attributes to draw the text on
my label, I'm just gonna create an attributedString.
So I'm gonna say, let attributedString equal. By
creating an attributedString with its constructor,
I want the one down here at the bottom.
It takes attributes and string. Okay, so
what you're gonna do for your Homework-2. I put the string,
it's just this string right here. And
attributes is these attributes I just created up there. And
then instead of saying flipCountLabel.text,
I say attributedText. And for a button, you would say set
attributedTitle for state instead of setTitle for
state and that equals this attributedString.
Okay, so that's all you need to do. So let's run this and
we're gonna see something a little bit kind of odd about
this, though. A little bit unexpected, I think.
So here we go. Hey, it didn't draw anything different.
Look at that, Flips: 0.
That looks exactly like before we made this change.
But, oh, look, if I click, now I'm getting the outlined font.
See how it's outlining my Flips?
So why when it first came up didn't this work, right here?
Yeah because this right here, this little =0,
this initialization, that does not cause the didSet to
happen. Okay, so that's an important thing to know.
When you initialize a var, it does not invoke the didSet,
only later settings of flipCount. So
how can we fix this? Well, I'm gonna take this and
put it in it's own little func. Okay, private func,
I'm gonna call it updateFlipCountLabel.
I'm gonna put that in there, and
I'm gonna call this updateFlipCountLabel in here.
updateFlipCountLabel, and
where's the other place I need to update the FlipCountLabel?
Well, here's another thing to learn that's kind of cool.
This, right here, is the label, right?
If you remember in our UI over here, that this right here
is connected up to that, right, it's connected. Now,
this connection gets made by iOS when you start up your UI,
right, it makes that connection.
Well, when it makes that connection, it's setting this.
So guess what, we can use didSet here.
When you have an outlet,
didSet does get called when that outlet gets set by iOS,
when this connection right here gets made, that gets
called. So here we can update our flipCountLabel here. Okay,
so now that flipCountLabel is gonna be updated when we first
connect that flip zero and also every time we change it
after that. Got it? All right, back to our slides. So,
you learned two things there, right? You learned that that
equal zero didn't cause didSet to happen and you learned that
on an outlet, you can didSet. You can set things because
that outlet just got hooked up for you.
All right, last really, really important thing here. We need
to really rush, because we're running out of time.
This is very important, this is about functions as types.
So I believe the supreme court a couple of years ago that
functions are people too. And so functions get the full
treatment of a type that any other type gets.
You can use a function as a type anywhere, all right? And
you do it just by declaring an argument to a function or
a var, whatever, to be of type function.
And you specify the arguments and
the return value of that function. So
it'll be a variable of that. So you can do this anywhere
a type is allowed. Let's look at an example. I have a var
here called operation. It is of type function that takes
a double and returns a double. So the syntax here is awesome.
It looks just like declaring a function that takes a double
and return it, just no names of arguments, but the types
are all in there. So this is how you declare a function.
You declare a var that is a function.
You can do it for variables, passing to functions,
parameters, everything. You can always do this. So
you can assign this var, it's exactly like you would think.
I'm gonna assign operation = sqrt. Okay,
sqrt is a function that takes a double and returns a double.
sqrt 是个函数，接受一个 Double，返回一个 Double
So it's perfectly legal for me to say operation = sqrt,
那么我写 operation = sqrt 是完全合法的
all right? And how do I call it? Well, I call it just like
那么我如何调用它呢？我可以就像
a function. Operation of 4.0 is gonna call, in this case,
调用一个函数一样调用它，在这个例子中 operation(4.0)
square root of 4.0, because operation is a function var,
会调用 sqrt(4.0) 因为 operation 是一个函数类型变量
that's holding a functioning.
它储存着一个函数
That function is square root, okay. Could not be simpler.
那个函数就是平方根。这很简单，对吧
Everybody cool with this? Now, other languages have function
所有人都懂了吧。其他语言中有
pointers and all this stuff, but it's all pretty tortuous
函数指针啥的，那些用起来都有些拐弯抹角的
to use. But in Swift, it's a first class citizen, okay.
但在 Swift 中，它就是“一等公民”
Functions are a first class citizen.
函数是“一等公民”
They will be the argument to many iOS methods,
它们会作为许多 iOS 函数的参数
functions will be. Okay, now a lot of times,
好的，那么大多数时候
the function you wanna past doesn't already exist.
你想作为参数传递的那个函数还不存在
So forces you to go write a function to pass in. For
那么它就要求你自己写一个函数来传递
example, let's say I had the function changeSign, okay. So
举个例子，比如说我需要函数 changeSign
there's no thing like square root that does change signs.
而我们并没有一个函数来实现改变符号，sqrt 也不会改变符号
So I have to write a really simple little function here,
所以我就需要在这里写一个非常简单的小函数
And all it does, it takes a double and returns a double,
它做的就是接受一个 Double 型并返回一个 Double 型
#TODO: 1318这里多了
changeSign.
just like square root. And it returns minus the operand.
就像 sqrt 一样。而它返回的是 -operand
So I'm changing the sign of the operand here. So I could
这样我就可以改变这个 operand 的符号了
use it in the same way. I've got an operation. I'll just
那么我就可以以同样的方式来使用它了，我这有 operation
say operation = changeSign instead of operation = sqrt.
我只用写 operation = changeSign，而不是 operation = sqrt
But this is kind of a lot of typing and
但只为了实现改变符号就来写一个函数
annoying to have to go create a whole function to do
的话要敲不少代码，而且有点令人厌烦
changeSign when all I want is for that thing to change sign.
因为我想做的就只是改变符号而已
So we can do, use what's called a closure.
那么我们可以使用闭包(closure)
How many people have heard the phrase closure,
有多少人听说过闭包
know what a closure is?
知道闭包是什么
Okay, about half of you again. Okay, so closure is really
好的，差不多你们当中的一半。那么闭包实际上
like an inlined function. It's a little special in that it
就像一个内联函数，它有点特别的就是它会
captures the state around it but it's essentially an inline
捕捉它周围的状态。但它本质上就是一个内联函数
function. So what does the syntax look like if we wanted
那么我们要用怎样的语法才能
to take changeSign and just drop it right into the middle
直接获取 changeSign 并将直接放在这段代码中呢
here instead of having a separate function? Okay,
而不是在另写一个函数
how would we do that? All right,
我们如何才能做到这一点呢
we're just gonna pick up all of changeSign except for
我们只需要选中除了名字的 changeSign 函数的全部
its name and move it down.
部分，并将它移下来
Watch, okay, so I just put it right in there. Now I
看，我就只用将它放在这里
do have to make one syntactic change here, very important.
那么我现在还要在改变一处语法，这很重要
I have to move that first curly brace, the one right
我必须要将这个第一个大括号
before the word return. I had to move it to beginning and
在 return 前面的那个，我要将它移到开始部分
replace it with the word in, so watch this happen.
并在它原来的位置用 in 代替，看好了
This moves to the front, put the word in. That's it though.
这个移到前面去，将 in 放进去，就是这样
Once you make that small syntactic change, you can drop
一旦你完成了这个小的语法改变，你就可以
any function right in there. But it gets much better on
将任何函数放在这里。我们这样做会更加的好
this because we have type inference in Swift. And Swift
因为在 Swift 中有类型推断
can absolutely go to town here because it knows a lot about
并且 Swift 在这里当然也会这么做，因为它非常了解
what's going on here. For example, Swift knows that this
这里正在发生着什么。比如说，Swift 知道这个
operation thing returns a double. It knows that, so
operation 返回一个 Double 型，它知道的。
you don't need to say returns double there, so just take
所以你不需要在这里写 return double，把它拿去
that out. it also knows that the operand is a double, so
就好了。Swift 也知道 operand 是 Double 型的
you don't need to say that that operand is a double,
所以你这里不需要写 operand 是 Double
you can take that out, right?
你可以把它也拿去
It also knows that this function returns something, so
Swift 也知道这个函数会返回某个东西
you don't need the keyword return minus operand there. So
所以你这里也不需要关键字 return -operand
we can take that out as well. Okay, and even more,
因此我们也可以将它拿去。还有
Swift knows you want to have these embedded functions all
Swift 知道你希望有这个内嵌函数
the time, and it's a little annoying to have to think up
而每次都要为那个参数取个名字
a name for the argument to this thing. Okay, that
也是有点令人厌烦的
operand word that I had to think up there. So it lets you
就是那个单词 operand，我还要去想它，因此 Swift允许你用
substitute $0 for the first one, $1 for the second, $3 for
$0 代替第一个参数，$1 代替第二个参数，$3（误：应为 $2） 代替
the third one. So I'm gonna replace operand there with $0.
第三个参数。那么我在这里可以用 $0 来代替 operand
And when I do that, I don't need the in anymore either.
那么如果我这样做了，我也不需要这个 in 了
Now you see the power of the closure. Okay,
现在你们见识到闭包的强大了
I wanted to have an operation that changes the sign.
当我想要一个操作来改变符号
And I barely had to type any more characters than
我基本上不用打比 changeSign 这个名字
the changeSign, just the curly braces around it. And that's
更多的代码，就只用大括号那些就可以了
still gonna do, operation 4.0 is still gonna do -4.0. Okay,
并且这样仍然可以改变符号，operation(4.0) 仍然会返回 -4.0
so you're gonna be using closures all the time, and
所以你会经常使用到闭包
you're gonna be using these $0, 1, $1, $2,
并且你也经常会用 $0, 1, $1, $2
as the argument names. And it's gonna make it so that you
来当做参数的名字。这样做的话
have to type very little code to put the things in.
你只用写很少的代码就能将想要的功能放进来
Now why do I want closures, why do I want functions as
那么为什么我想要闭包呢
arguments? Well, it's usually because you,
为什么我想要函数能当做参数？那是因为
you're passing something to a function that wants to know
你时常要向一个函数传递一个参数，它才知道要
what to do. A function is a great way to tell it what to
做什么。那么用一个作为参数的函数是告诉它要做什么的很好的方式
do. Now why might it want to know what to do? Well,
那么那个函数想要知道自己该做什么呢
maybe it wants to know what to do if there's an error.
也许它想知道当出现了一个错误的时候自己该做什么
I'm gonna do something, it might generate an error, and
我会做某些事情，它可能会产生一个错误
I want to call a function in case there's an error so
那么当产生错误的时候，我希望调用一个函数
you can handle this function. Maybe it wants to know what to
来处理这个错误。那个函数也许想知道如果
do if it's gonna do something that takes a long time.
它要做一个很消耗时间的事情时该做什么
It's gonna go on the network and
比如说上网
download something off in the background and when it's done,
并在后台下载某些东西的时候，当下载完成后
it wants to tell you. Okay, we call a function to do that.
它想要告诉你。那么我们可以调用一个函数来做到这一点
Another thing is, it might be doing something repeatedly,
另外一件事是，它可能将会重复做某件事
it wants to do the same thing over and over. So it's asking
它想重复地做同样一件事，那么它就会
you to tell it what to do over and over. So let's take a look
问你要重复做什么事情。让我来看
at an example of that last one there, doing something over
最后的一个例子，我们要重复地做
and over. So array, naturally, it's a collection.
某些事情。那么，数组在本质上是一个集合
Well anyway, array has a method called map. And
数组有一个叫做 map 的函数
what map does, it takes only one argument, a function. And
而 map 做的就是，它接收一个参数，一个函数
it applies that function to every element in the array and
并且它对数组内的每个元素为参数调用那个函数
creates a new array. So
并创建一个新的数组
map returns a new array where every element in the array you
所以 map 会返回一个新的数组，它其中的每个元素
send it to gets operated on by some function.
就是以传入的那个函数对原数组每个元素运算后的返回值
In other words, it's a way to pass a function into array and
换句话说，这就是一种向数组中传入一个函数
tell it to do it on every element. Okay,
并用它运算在数组中每个元素的方法
that's what map does, so how does that work? Here I have
那就是 map 的功能，那么这是如何实现的呢
an array of floating point numbers. They happen to be
这里我有一个由浮点数组成的数组，它碰巧是
the first 5 prime numbers, right, 2, 3, 5, 7, 11 here.
前五个素数，对吧，2，3，5，7，11
And what if I wanted to have an array of all negative 2,
那么如果我想要一个由 -2，-3 那些
negative 3? Well I would just say negativePrimes =
组成的数组，我只用写 negativePrimes = prime.map( )
prime.map, the only argument is a function that does change
map 函数的唯一一个参数
sign, right? Just like we had on the previous slide,
就是用来改变符号的，对吧，它就像我们上一张幻灯片中的一样
change sign. And now we're getting a new array,
改变了符号。这样我们就得到了一个新的数组
negativePrimes is gonna be a new array with -2, -3, -5.
negativePrimes 就是一个包含 -2,-3,-5 的新数组
You see how I used map there? Now, list another example,
你看到我在这里是如何使用 map 了吧，另一个例子
maybe inverting the primes. So I'm gonna propriate
我想要得到这些数组的倒数
the closure, 1.0 divided by $0. Now I get 0.5, 0.33,
那么我就要改变这个闭包为 1.0 / $0，那我就会得到 0.5, 0.33
maybe I even want to convert it to a string.
也许我甚至想要将它转换为一个字符串
Perfectly legal, doesn't have to be the same type.
这是完全合法的，新的数组不一定要和老数组为同一个类型
I can return array of string. Now notice the yellow
我可以返回一个字符串的数组，现在注意到上面这些黄色的代码
things up there, changed a little with each line. You see
它们在各行是有些不同的
the first one map parentheses the closure. The next one
第一行闭包在小括号内
map open parentheses, closed parentheses then the closure.
第二行是 map() 后接着闭包
And the third one map, no parentheses and the closure.
在第三行中，map 后面没有小括号，紧接的就是闭包
Okay, this is using what's called trailing closure
这里是用的一个叫做 尾随闭包（trailing closure）
syntax, okay, we almost always use this. The rule here is,
的语法，我们基本上总是会这么用
if the last argument to any function is a closure,
它的规则是，如果一个函数的最后一个参数是闭包
you can move the closure outside the parenthesis of
你就可以将那个闭包移动到那些参数所在
the arguments. So see in the second line, inverted primes?
的小括号外面。看这里的第二行，当我们要去素数的倒数时
How I moved the closure outside? And furthermore,
我就把闭包移到括号外面去了
if it's the only argument,
还有，如果闭包是唯一一个参数
then you can just get rid of the parentheses entirely.
那么你就完全可以直接不写小括号
That's the third line, okay. And this is just to make our
就像第三行所展示的那样
code look nice. So we don't have extraneous parenthesis in
这样做就可以让我们的代码更好看。这样我们就可以将
there that we don't, beccause we've got the curly braces,
我们不需要的小括号去掉了。因为我们这里已经有大括号了
we kind of don't need those parentheses. Okay,
我们就不是很需要那些小括号了
so you'll see that in iOS when an argument to a function
那么你就会在 iOS 开发中看到，当一个函数的
is a function, it'll usually be the last argument. So
参数是一个函数时，它通常会是最后一个参数
that you can move it outside if you want.
这样如果你想的话，你就可以将它拿到外面
It's optional, you don't have to.
这是可选的，你不一定要这样做
All three of those are perfectly valid syntax right
这里的三种语法都是完全合法的
there. Okay, another cool use of closures,
好的，闭包的另一个很酷的用处
property initialization. What if you have a property and
在与属性初始化（property initialization），如果你有一个属性
you wanna initialize it to something but
并且你想将它初始化为某个东西
it's not like you just can't do one line thing, right.
但你不能以一行就搞定它
You can't say equals five or equals something simple. You
你不能就像写 =22 或等于其他什么这样简单
need to do two or three lines of code to get it initialized.
你需要两三行代码才能将它初始化
No problem, you're allowed to set the property equal to
没问题，你可以将这个属性赋值为一个
executing a closure. Now that closure is automatically
要执行的闭包，那么这个闭包自动地就会是
going to be a closure that takes no arguments and
一个不接受任何参数
returns the right type to initialize that property.
并且返回一个恰当类型，能初始化这个属性的闭包
So you can do anything you want in that closure and
所以你在这个闭包中可以做任何你想做的事情
just return something of the right type. And
只需要在最后返回一个正确的类型的值
then you execute it right away with open parenthesis, closed
接着你用 () 来立即执行它
parenthesis. See how there's the little open parenthesis,
看到这里的小括号了吗
closed parenthesis there right at the end of the closure?
它们就在这个闭包的后面
That's just gonna execute that closure right there.
它们就会在那里立即执行这个闭包
This is especially cool with lazy properties. Because it
这用在 lazy 属性中就很棒
means, this closure won't be executed until someone asks
因为这表示着，在这个属性被访问之前
for this property. Okay, so
这个闭包就不会执行
you're combining lazy in the closures. So
那么你就将 lazy 和闭包联系了起来
closures really cool for initializing properties. Now,
所以说闭包在初始化属性的时候非常有用
one thing about closures to be careful of.
而关于闭包值得警惕的一点是
They do capture their surrounding variables.
它们会捕捉它们周围的变量
So if I have a closure, it's just a function embedded right
所以如果我有一个闭包，它就是一个嵌在我的代码中的
in my code. If there are local variables, or
函数，如果在闭包所在的这个类中有局部变量
instance variables in the class I'm in, or whatever, and
或者实例变量，或者其他什么
I use them in the closure it works. And even if that
我就可以在闭包中使用它们。并且甚至当
closure sticks around, those things still continue to work
那个闭包被到处传递时，那些变量也仍然是有效的
until the closure goes away. What this means, though,
直到我的闭包消失。这就意味着
since closures are types and they can put in arrays and
闭包是类型，并且它们可以被装进数组和字典中
dictionaries, closures are reference types.
闭包是引用类型
There's only two reference types in Swift, classes and
Swift 中只有两种引用类型，类和闭包
closures. So what does that mean?
这意味着什么
It means this closure gets put in the heap if you put it in
这意味着当你将闭包装入数组时，它就被压入了堆中
an array. So that array actually has pointers to this
那么这个数组实际上是有指向这个闭包的指针
closure. Now this is a little mind bending. I don't expect
这里有一点绕弯子。
you to get this right at the top. But it also means that,
我不要求你们现在马上就理解。但这也意味着
if you capture variables in your closure from your
如果闭包捕获了它周围代码
surrounding code, they have to go live in the heap too.
中的变量，它们也要被存入堆中
Because we can't have this closure not function, right?
因为我们不能让这个闭包错误地工作
Can't if this function has to be a function that executes.
这个闭包必须要是一个可以执行的函数
So here's an example of that.
这里有一个例子
Here I have a local variable called ltaue,
我这里有一个叫做 ltuae 的变量
life the universe and everything,
生命，宇宙，和其他一切
I think that stands for. It's set to 42. Okay,
大概是这个意思，它被赋值为42
and my operation, the closure there, says ltuae times $0. So
并且我的函数也就是这个闭包中写着 ltuae * $0
that closure is actually using a local variable inside it.
这个闭包实际上在它其中使用着一个局部变量
Now what happens if I put that operation in an array? Okay,
那么当我将这个 operation 放入数组中会发生什么
and then later go back and get it out of the array, and
我之后还会从数组中将它取出并
execute it. Well, when it does that, ltuae still needs to be
执行它。那么为了能做到这一点，ltuae 仍然需要
there. Because otherwise, the closure won't execute. So
在我们的堆中，否在的话闭包无法执行
ltuau, the ltuae gets captured into the heap and
那么 ltuae 就会被捕获到堆中
stays there until the closure goes away.
并且待在堆中，直到闭包离开堆
Now, this is awesome, it all just works magically.
这很棒，它奇迹般地就可以工作了
You don't have to think about it, except in one case, and
你不用去考虑它，出来在一种情况下
that's a memory cycle.
就是引用循环（memory cycle）
This can create a memory cycle because you might capture
这可能会生成一个引用循环，因为你有可能会捕获
the class that array of operations is in. Okay,
装有 operation 的数组所在的集合
if you capture the class that array is of operations in,
如果你捕获了装有 operation 的数组所在的集合
then this closure has captured that class into the heap. And
闭包接着将那个类捕获进堆
that class through its array is captured
并且那个类通过它其中的数组
the closure in the heap. So
也将闭包捕获进了堆
they're pointing to each other through the array,
以数组为中介，它们在指向对方
you see? They're creating a memory cycle, that closure is
你能理解吗，它们这样就产生了引用循环
keeping the class, the class is keeping the closure.
闭包将类留在堆中，类将闭包留在堆中
They're staying in the heap,
they can never leave until someone removes that closure
from this array, for example. So,
we can break closure cycles like these. We use that thing,
I talked about last time, unowned. Remember, unowned?
When we talked about weak and strong and unowned.
And I said, I'll tell you what unowned is. So
I'm gonna put these two things together. Unowned and
the fact that we can have these cycles. In a couple of
weeks, I'll talk to you, how we break these cycles. Okay,
how we can create a closure that will not keep
something else in. Okay so, let's see a demo of closures.
I'm gonna improve the method index of the one and only face
card to be way better. And not only am I gonna use closures,
I'm gonna go back and use extensions to protocols, and
I'm gonna tie this all together. Okay, so
lets do that. Over here, if we remember,
our, we'll make it one big window here. If we go
back to our concentration, all right, here's concentration.
Remember we had index of one and only face card,
which, supposedly made our code simpler,
which it did down here. It made this code really
beautiful and readable down here. But, it actually added
quite a bit of code here. But this is way more code than you
actually need To find the index of the oneAndOnly
face card, if you use a method that takes a closure. Now,
the method we're gonna use, it's kinda like map,
its own collection, it's called filter. So what filter
does is it goes through every item in the collection and
executes a function that you provide. Filter only has one
argument. It's a function. That function returns a bool.
So it executes that function with the argument being each
item in the collection. If that function returns true,
then it puts it in a new array, okay, and
if it turns false, it doesn't. So essentially
filters the collection into an array, but only the ones that
return true from the function. See what I'm saying? So
that's why it's called filter. Filters the collection,
makes an array out of the ones that return true. Well,
that's great for this, because index of oneAndOnly face card.
How about I go look at all the indexes of the cards and
just find the indexes that have face up cards? So I just
need a function that says whether a card's face up and
I can do it. So let's do that. I'm gonna let index, we'll say
the let the face up card indices I'll call it, okay,
this is gonna be an array. I'm gonna let it equal to my card
indices. Card indices, what type is card indices,
anyone remember? Oh I just showed you what it was.
Right, right? It's accountable range of int. It indexes into
the cards array. So I'm gonna filter those indices by
providing a function. And it's the only argument, so
I don't need any parentheses or
anything, I'm just gonna put it after. This function just
needs to look at the index and see if that's a face up card.
So that's cards sub the index, we'll just use $0,
which is the one argumentative function, isFaceup. Okay,
so that's a Boolean function, right here.
This is a Boolean function, executed by a closure, right
in there that returns true, if the card of that index is face
up. So, now I've created this which is an array,
it's an array of array indexes by the way.
Let's take a look, see. Array of array indexes.
This type Array.Index, remember, we had String.Index,
Array.Index, is type aliased or just set equal to be int.
That's why arrays can be indexed by int,
cuz their Array.Index is int. That's not true for strings.
String.Index, unfortunately, is not int. Okay, so
this is an array of all the indices. Now, if this only has
one thing in it then we have one face up card.
We all agree with that? So I'm just gonna return here,
that if faceUpCardIndices.count ==1,
I am going to return the faceUpCardIndices.first,
first is just a collection method that returns the first
thing in the collection. Otherwise, I'm gonna return
nil, because we either have zero face up cards or
we have more than one, in either case, we'll return 0.
So I don't need any of this stuff right here. Okay,
so this is a lot cleaner than this whole thing.
Everybody agree with that? And a little more readable too.
Give me all the face card indices by filtering
the indices to show me the ones that are face up. Okay,
it kind of reads a little better as well, but
we can do better than this even.
And we're gonna do better by creating an extension to
a protocol down here. The protocol we're gonna extend is
collection. So we're gonna add a var. Could be a function,
but it's gonna be a var to collection.
So, I'm gonna be adding it to string, dictionary,
array, all these things. And what it's gonna do,
it's gonna be the oneAndOnly. And it's gonna return
the one and only thing in that collection, if there's only
one thing in the collection or it's gonna return nil.
Now, what is the type,
of oneAndOnly gonna be? Well, collection is a generic type.
And it has one of its generic things as element,
which is the type of the thing in there. So element is just
like a placeholder, right, in the array of element.
You recognize that? For in a generic type, it's the type.
And of course I want it to be optional.
Because I'm only gonna return non nil, if there's one and
only one thing in this collection, this string, or
this array, or this dictionary, or
this countable range.
And here's how I can implement it, watch this. Return count
== 1? first : nil. Now how am I able to do this?
Well count is a collection method, tells how many things
in there. first is a collection method, it returns
the first thing in there. So since these are collection
methods, I can use them in the implementation of a collection
var. Seeing the power here of these extensions on protocols.
And now, strings, arrays, countable ranges,
they all implement oneAndOnly. So I can go back up here and
just return, Return this, remember, it's an array
of the indices of face up cards, dot oneAndOnly.
Okay, and I don't even need this. Okay, even simpler.
By the way, I could absolutely do, let ch
= hello.oneAndOnly. Okay, now that would return what?
What would ch be equal to there? Anybody?
>> It would be nil,
because oneAndOnly returns if there's one and only one
element and this string has five elements. If I did this,
what would this return? This will return h, the one and
only thing in that string. So I got that by
extending collection, which string and array happen to be.
What's the type of this, by the way? ch,
what do you think its type is? It's an optional character.
Optional character because the elements of a string are
characters. And a string is a collection of characters. But
if I click on it, it's gonna say, it's a String.Element.
So just like Array.Index is type alias to be int,
String.Element is type alias to be character.
So, you have to look in the documentation to see that or
you just have to know it.
But if you're doing your Alt clicking, I don't want you
to be surprised when you see that's not a character.
Okay, all right, so a lot of things went on in just this
short demo here. We used the closure right here. And
we also extended a protocol right here to create this
method here. So hopefully you understand both of those.
If you don't, use Piazza, come up and ask me afterwards or
whatever. All right, see you next time. Oh,
wait, sorry one thing, let me go back and
just show you the coming up. Because there is one thing to
note here about the coming up. Which is that Friday,
we were gonna have the optional section
object persistence, we're not gonna do that this Friday.
We'll do it in a future Friday,
we will do object persistence but in a future Friday.
So, there's no Friday section at all this week. Next week,
I will be doing views, gestures, multi-touch,
multiple MVCs, all that. >> For more,
please visit us at Stanford.edu.
>> 更多课程详见 stanford.edu